<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The court of conscience: or, Iosephs brethrens iudgement barre. By Thomas Barnes</title>
            <author>Barnes, Thomas, Minister of St. Margaret's, New Fish Street, London.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1623</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 155 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 83 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04629</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1475</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114798</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850021</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850021</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15204</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04629)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15204)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 824:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The court of conscience: or, Iosephs brethrens iudgement barre. By Thomas Barnes</title>
                  <author>Barnes, Thomas, Minister of St. Margaret's, New Fish Street, London.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 88, folded plates   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Davvson for Nathanael Newbery, and are to be sold at the Star vnder St. Peters Church in Corne-hill and Popes-head Alley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1623.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Conscience --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15204:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15204:1"/>
            <p>THE COVRT OF CONSCIENCE: <hi>OR, IOSEPHS</hi> BRETHRENS IVDGEMENT BARRE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>BY</hi> THOMAS BARNES.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2. COR. 1.12.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Our reioycing is this, the teſtimonie of our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, that in ſimplicitie and godly ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, &amp;c.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>The guiltineſſe of the conſcience is the mother of feare. <bibl>
                     <hi>Chryſoſt.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by IOHN DAVVSON for <hi>Nathaniel Newbery,</hi> and are to be ſold at the Star vnder S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Peters</hi> Church in Corne-hill and Popes-head Alley. 1623.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:15204:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15204:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL WILLIAM TOWSE Sergeant at Law, one of His MAIESTIES Iuſtice of Peace in <hi>Eſſex:</hi> As alſo to the Right Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, the Lady KATHERINE BARNARDISTON, his beloued Wife, both my much reſpected friends. The Author wiſheth the bleſſings of this life and the next.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was a ſaying of one of the<note n="a" place="margin">Ambr. an Conſtan. Duo ſunt tibi ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaria, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientia &amp; fama, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientia prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter te, fama propter proximu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, in an Epiſtle to one of his friends: <hi>Two things are needfull for thee,
<pb facs="tcp:15204:3"/> conſcience, and credite, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience for thy ſelfe, credite for thy neighbour.</hi> And not without reaſon ſpake he this; for the one is an inward witneſſe, the other giues an outward teſtimony of our doings. The one ſerues to breed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward conſolation, the other to bring outward commendation. But not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the neceſsitie of both, yet the beſt of the two is leaſt regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, the Philoſophers ſaying being most true:<note n="b" place="margin">Senec. de morib. Plerique fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientiam autem pauci verentur.</note> 
               <hi>Many feare their credite, but few their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</hi> So it fared (as it ſeemes) with thoſe ten ſonnes of holy <hi>Iacob,</hi> who did miſ-uſe his beloued <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph:</hi> So they might hide that wrong they did their brother, and ſaue their credite with their father,
<pb facs="tcp:15204:3"/> little cared they (vntill diſtreſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waked them) how matters ſtood in the Court within them. So alſo it fares with the <hi>Secret ſinners,</hi> and <hi>Ciuill liuers</hi> of our dayes. To keepe their name good amongst men they are very curious, but to haue a cleere witneſſe in their owne conſcience, they are nothing ſtudious. That this euill might be ſomewhat helped, this Treatiſe haue I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piled; wherein my ſcope is to bring men to a care of their <hi>Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences</hi> as well as their names, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the one to be as needfull to cleere them from blame before the Barre of heauen, as the other to keepe them from ſhame amongst <hi>men.</hi> For (if <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith true)
<pb facs="tcp:15204:4"/> though <hi>a good name be bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then a precious oynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Eccl. 7.1.</note> Yet, <hi>A good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is a continuall ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Prou. 15.15.</note>. If any one aske the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of this my drift: my reaſon is two-fold. Firſt, becauſe conſcience is fearefull in accuſing. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, becauſe conſcience is faithfull in recording: which two things (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst others, according to the tenour of the text) are principally and moſt largely handled in this Treatiſe. And good I deſire all may doe in, and to the Iſrael of God.</p>
            <p>To your Worſhips I thought good to dedicate the ſame: though wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thier papers were fitter for your Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage. If I were not confident of
<pb facs="tcp:15204:4"/> acceptation: I ſhould not preſume to preſent you with it. Albeit, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede it had beene fit that my firſt friends, ſhould haue had my firſt fruits, yet I hope my ſecond pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like labours in this kinde, will not be vnwelcome. Howſoeuer, I owe them, your Worſhips vndeſerued fauours ſhowne mee, challenge the ſame, and more at my hands. If you pleaſe to vouchſafe them the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding. I doubt not but you ſhall finde ſomething profitable, though plainly deliuered in an homely ſtile. If you pleaſe to afford them the protection, being ſo ſimple and ſmall as they are, you ſhall get me into ſtronger bonds, continually to wiſh to both your Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, what <hi>Iohn</hi> did on the behalfe
<pb facs="tcp:15204:5"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:15204:5"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:15204:6"/> of the <hi>Elect Ladie,</hi> and No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Gaius,</hi> euen to your ſoules: <hi>Grace, peace and mercie</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">2. Ioh. 3.</note>: to your bodies <hi>health and proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peritie</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">3. Ioh. 2.</note>: For which he promiſeth to pray, who is</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Worſhips at command, in and for the Lord. THOMAS BARNES.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:15204:6"/>
            <head>The Table of the firſt part,</head>
            <list>
               <item>In this text are two parts,
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>1.</hi> Certaine Accuſers touching whom note
<list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>1.</hi> The occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that brought them in, in this word AND, wherein
<list>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>1.</hi> The meaning, <hi>pag. 1.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>2.</hi> The <hi>1.</hi> Doctrine of the text, that <hi>affliction doth oft awake conſcience, and mooue to confeſſion,</hi> pag. <hi>6.</hi> where
<list>
                                       <item>
                                          <hi>1.</hi> Proofe. <hi>pag. 8.</hi>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>
                                          <hi>2.</hi> Vſe threefold.
<list>
                                             <item>
                                                <hi>1.</hi> Reproofe. <hi>pag. 12.</hi>
                                             </item>
                                             <item>
                                                <hi>2.</hi> Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation two-fold,
<list>
                                                   <item>
                                                      <hi>1.</hi> To make a right vſe of affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. <hi>p. 14.</hi>
                                                   </item>
                                                   <item>
                                                      <hi>2.</hi> To be patient in affliction. <hi>p. 19.</hi>
                                                   </item>
                                                </list>
                                             </item>
                                             <item>
                                                <hi>3.</hi> Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of <hi>2.</hi> things,
<list>
                                                   <item>
                                                      <hi>1.</hi> Why God af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicteth his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. <hi>p. 17.</hi>
                                                   </item>
                                                   <item>
                                                      <hi>2.</hi> That God by affliction will haue glorie from the reprobate. <hi>page. 18.</hi>
                                                   </item>
                                                </list>
                                             </item>
                                          </list>
                                       </item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>2.</hi> What man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of perſons theſe <hi>accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers</hi> were, <hi>They ſaid one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> where
<list>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>1.</hi> The meaning. <hi>pag 6.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>2.</hi> The <hi>2.</hi> doctrine of the Text. <hi>That co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                                       <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience accuſeth.</hi> wherein
<list>
                                       <item>
                                          <hi>1.</hi> Proofe. <hi>pag. 21.</hi>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>
                                          <hi>2.</hi> An obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. <hi>pag. 23.</hi>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>
                                          <hi>3.</hi> A doubt remooued, <hi>p. 26.</hi>
                                          <list>
                                             <item>
                                                <hi>1.</hi> Confutation. <hi>pag. 31.</hi>
                                             </item>
                                             <item>
                                                <hi>2.</hi> Conſolation. <hi>pag. 35.</hi>
                                             </item>
                                             <item>
                                                <hi>3.</hi> Terrour <hi>pag. 42.</hi>
                                             </item>
                                             <item>
                                                <hi>4.</hi> Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation both to get and keep a good conſcience, <hi>pag. 47.</hi> where are alſo ſet downe helpes.
<list>
                                                   <item>
                                                      <hi>1.</hi> To get a good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and to be cured of a bad. <hi>pag. 50.</hi>
                                                   </item>
                                                   <item>
                                                      <hi>2.</hi> To keepe a good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and to be kept from an euill. <hi>pag. 62.</hi>
                                                   </item>
                                                </list>
                                             </item>
                                          </list>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>
                                          <hi>4.</hi> Vſe foure fold.</item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:15204:7"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:15204:7"/>
            <head>
               <hi>THE COVRT OF CONSCIENCE:</hi> OR, <hi>IOSEPHS BRETHRENS IVDGEMENT BARRE.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>GEN. 42.21.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And they ſaid one to another, We are verily guilty concerning our bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in that we ſaw the anguiſh of his ſoule, when he beſought vs, and we would not heare: therefore is this diſtreſſe come vpon vs.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Or to trouble you with any tedious Preface:<note place="margin">The ſumme and ſcope of the Text.</note> this Scripture being giuen by inſpiration (as all diuine Scripture is,) and written for our learning, doth
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:15204:8"/> comprehend in it a Iudiciall act of <hi>Diuine</hi> prouidence, in bringing to iudgement that ſame miſchieuous fact committed by ten of <hi>Iacobs</hi> ſonnes, againſt <hi>Ioſeph</hi> their inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, and harmeleſſe brother.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</note>In which act (as it ordinarily falles out in Iudiciall caſes,) two circumſtances offer themſelues to our conſideration.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The accuſers at this Barre.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The accuſation it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>The firſt is laide downe in the beginning of the verſe. <hi>And they ſaid one to another.</hi> The ſecond in the clauſe of the verſe, <hi>we are veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly guiltie concerning our brother, in that we ſaw the anguiſh of his ſoule, when he beſought vs, and we would not heare, therefore is this distreſſe come vpon vs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The firſt part ſubdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided and interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</note>Touching the firſt (which wee muſt firſt handle) we may note two particulars. Firſt the occaſion that
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:15204:8"/> mooued the accuſers to come in: Secondly, the perſons, who theſe accuſers were.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The occaſion is gathered out of the precedent verſes, and coupled to the text by this particle, ſo that in this one word <hi>AND,</hi> the occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is intimated, which ſtands thus.</p>
            <p>A great dearth in <hi>Iacobs</hi> dayes, raigneth in all the lands about E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt: And (as it is the lot of Gods deareſt ſeruants, to be common ſharers with other in common ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities) that good old father with his whole family was pinched with it, as well as other places. At which pinch, hearing of a great Corne-maſter in Egypt (little thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king it had beene his ſonne <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> for whom he had laide aſide his mourning weede ſo long agoe) he calles his ten ſonnes vnto him, commands them to haſten into E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt, to this man: to buy and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:15204:9"/> bring home ſome foode for his houſhold. At his command, thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they ſpeede themſelues; whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, no ſooner were they come, but this Gouernour (their brother <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> whom they had once miſ-uſed, though neuer dreaming it ſhould be hee) ſeemes (in an holy policie to vſe them harſhly,<note n="a" place="margin">Verſe 9.</note> char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth them to be Spies, would not accept of the<note n="b" place="margin">Verſ. 10, 11, 12, 13, 14.</note> Apologie they made for themſelues, putteth them into Ward three dayes,<note n="c" place="margin">Verſ. 17.</note> would not ſuffer them to goe home with corne (for which they came; but on condition, that one of them ſhould remaine his priſoner, vntill the reſt went home and fetcht their brother <hi>Beniamin,</hi> (whom they had ſpoke off) to bring him to him<note n="d" place="margin">Verſ. 15.19.20.</note>.</p>
            <p>Theſe brethren meeting with this harſh and vnexpected enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment, begin to be ſomewhat
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:15204:9"/> troubled in their mindes, and each one by his countenance (as it is likely) coniecturing, and gueſſing at the diſturbed motions in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers minde, by reaſon of theſe ſtraights, fall to that parley a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt themſelues, which is recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the preſent text.<note place="margin">The ſenſe of the word <hi>And.</hi>
               </note> Now then if any ſhall aske, wherefore this word <hi>[And]</hi> ſerues in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the text, when as there is no ſentence before, to be fitly ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to this ſpeech. I anſwer, though it doth not ioyne words and ſentences, or ſentence and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence together: yet it coupleth minde and mouth, fore-going thoughts, and follow words, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying that ſuch thoughts as aroſe in their minds about <hi>Ioſephs</hi> vſage of them, gaue the occaſion, and produced thoſe words of accuſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which the text hath in it. So is the occaſion: The parties who
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:15204:10"/> brought in the accuſation (in theſe words, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
               <hi>They ſaid one to another,</hi>) you vnderſtand already, to be the tenne ſonnes of <hi>Iacob, Iudah, Simeon, Leui, Dan</hi> and the reſt, each ones proper conſcience by this occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, bringing in a ſeuerall indite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt himſelfe, for the wrong formerly offered vnto <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hence then we haue two leſſons to take forth.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>That afflictions are of notable vſe to awake the conſcience, and make a man confeſſe his faults.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>That an euill conſcience is an accuſing conſcience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>1</label> For the firſt, it is as plaine in the text, as you would wiſh.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Diſtreſſe doth occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion many times touch of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and confeſſion of ſinnes.</note>Theſe brethren of <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing dealt moſt vnnaturally with him their brother, lay a ſleepe in that ſinne of theirs, ſo long as the day of proſperitie laſted, without
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:15204:10"/> any compunction of conſcience for it, without making any confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of it: But now when they ſee themſelues in great diſtreſſe, pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched with penury at home, vſed hardly abroad, where they hoped for the ſupply of their wants, thruſt into priſon, charged falſely to bee ſpies, could not (in their own thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king) be beleeued, when they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend themſelues; now I ſay that they perceiue themſelues in theſe ſtraits, they begin to buckle, the conſcience is pricked, and the fault is confeſſed mutually a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt themſelues; which before (as it is like) they were more ready to laugh at, then grieue for. Put a malefactor deſeruedly vpon the racke,<note place="margin">A ſimile.</note> and you ſhall get that from him in confeſſion, which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe he purpoſed neuer to haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed. So let but afflictions racke the body many times, ſinne will
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:15204:11"/> racke the ſoule, and the tongue will confeſſe the guiltineſſe of the heart. Examples, both of Elect, and Reprobate, may be produced for the proofe of this.</p>
            <p>Firſt, concerning the Elect, how afflictions haue thus wrought with them, the example of <hi>Ionah</hi> doth declare. So long as he was let alone, he diſobeyed the voyce of God, fled from the face of God, and ſlept ſpiritually in the bottome of his ſinne, as corporally in the bottome of the ſhippe, but when the Lord ſhook the ſhippe wherein he was, with the violence of the winde; threatned preſent deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to him, and all thoſe that were with him in the ſhippe; then he could cry out, and confeſſe, <hi>for my ſake, for my ſinne, this great tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt is vpon you</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Ion. 1.12.</note>. Memorable and not vnknowne, is the ſtory of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſeh:</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">2. Chron. 33. from the 1. verſe to the 14.</note> Who in the time of his
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:15204:11"/> proſperity, raigning in his pompe, rebelled againſt the God of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, reared vp the Altars of <hi>Baal, made groues to worſhip the whole Hoſt of heauen, ſacrificed his children to Moloch, obſerued times, vſed inchant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, followed witch-craft, dealt with familiar ſpirits, wrought much euill himſelfe in the ſight of the Lord, made his ſubiects to erre, and to doe worſe then the heathen;</hi> And ſo long as his peace laſted, wee doe not reade that euer he confeſſed one of his abhominations to God, or to man, in token of any remorſe for the ſame. <hi>But when the Lord brought the Captaines of the Hoſt of the King of Aſſyria vpon him, who tooke him among the thornes, bound him with fetters, carried him into Babylon, and when he was thus in affliction, then he could beſeech the Lord, humble him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe before the God of his fathers, and pray vnto him; and ſo by conſequent</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:15204:12"/> make confeſſion of his ſinnes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him. <hi>Dauids mouth ſhall alſo teach</hi> this truth.<note n="c" place="margin">Pſal. 32.</note> 
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32. <hi>Day and night (ſaith hee in the</hi> 4. <hi>verſe) thy hand was heauy vpon mee;</hi> and marke what followeth in the 5. <hi>verſe. I acknowledged my ſinne vnto thee, mine iniquitie did I not hide.</hi> Yea, affliction will mooue the mindes, and extort confeſſion from the mouthes of Reprobates alſo. The the thunder and haile, and iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>of locusts</hi> vpon Egypt, <hi>can make Pharaoh himſelfe to confeſſe, and ſay, I haue ſinned this time, the Lord is righteous; I and my people are wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Exod. 9.27.</note>. <hi>I haue ſinned against the Lord your God, and againſt you</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Cha. 10.16.</note>. The ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry newes and tydings of affliction to come, vpon <hi>Ahab, his wife,</hi> and poſterity, can make <hi>Ahab, (though he were one, that ſold himſelfe to work wickedneſſe in the ſight of the Lord) yet euen to rend his cloathes, put ſacke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloath
<pb facs="tcp:15204:12"/> vpon his fleſh, faſt and goe ſoft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">1. King. 21 from the 21. verſ. to the 28.</note> 
               <hi>and confeſſe his iniquitie:</hi> Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much, that we may truly ſay of a great many, that their dayes of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction are their<note n="g" place="margin">Beat. Rhen. an. in Tert. l. de patien. p. <hi>2.</hi> Natales agnitiones.</note> 
               <hi>birth-dayes of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>1</label> And good reaſon for it; for why afflictions in themſelues are fruits of ſinne: had not ſinne entred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the world, neither could diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, diſgraces, pouerties, captiuity, croſſes, and loſſes, haue befallen mortall man, but ſinne ouer-ſprea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all, and ſo afflictions, as fruits of ſinne, being incident vnto all; when men are vnder affliction, they will acknowledge their tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions, as the cauſe of the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>2</label> Secondly, afflictions, as one calles them, are a practicall law<note n="h" place="margin">Paraeus in Gen. Col. <hi>2029.</hi> Affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiones ſunt lex practica.</note>. Now without the law, <hi>Sinne is dead,</hi> not perceiued, as the Apoſtle ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth,<note n="i" place="margin">Rom. 7.9.</note> But when the law commeth, is when a ſenſe of Gods wrath is
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:15204:13"/> ſtirred vp in vs, not onely by the preaching of the law, but alſo by afflictions, then <hi>ſinne reuiueth,</hi> as the ſame Apoſtle ſheweth, is felt and called to minde, which being recorded, is alſo confeſſed. For though the confeſſion of ſin doth not alwayes follow the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of it, yet the remembrance of it, doth alwaies goe before the acknowledgement of it.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> What occaſion to complaine, doth this point offer vs,<note place="margin">Reproofe of thoſe that are ſenſeleſſe of ſinne in the time of affliction.</note> of the ſenſeleſneſſe and ſtupidity of thoſe who lye vnder the burthen of affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, hauing the hand of God vpon them moſt grieuouſly, ſome in their bodies, ſome in their name, ſome in their eſtate, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times poſitiuely exerciſed with the preſence of iudgements, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times priuatiuely viſited with the depriuation of outward benefits, and yet all will not auaile to worke
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:15204:13"/> vpon their conſciences, and to make them confeſſe their ſinnes, acknowledge their abhominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons before the Maieſtie of heauen; Nay, they will rather iuſtifie them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, as if they were wronged by God, and had not deſerued ſuch ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerity of puniſhment. How, or how doth affliction looſe its force in them? how vnuſefull is the day of aduerſitie, to ſuch ſenſeleſſe ones? it is a ſigne that that man is of a deſperate diſpoſition, and in a deſperate condition, whom troubles and croſſes, which are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny for the number, weightie in meaſure, not light in qualitie, not ſmall in quantitie, can worke no contrition; can, wring no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion from. This is that which made the Lord, ſo pathetically in the mouth of one of his Prophets, expoſtulate with the hard-hearted and rebellious Iſraelites. <hi>Why ſhould
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:15204:14"/> yee be ſtricken any more? yet the more I ſmite you, the more you ſinne againſt mee:</hi> as farre as I can ſee; as bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits cannot draw you to contriti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, no more can my rod bring you to confeſſion. In another Prophet, thus he ſpeakes. <hi>In vaine haue I ſmitten your children, they receiued no correstion</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Ierm. 2.30.</note>. What an heauy caſe is this, that this, euen this, brings God into ſuch controuerſie with his owne people, whom by exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall priuiledges, hee had viſibly married vnto himſelfe? What? not in aduerſitie ſeeke the Lord<note n="m" place="margin">Hoſ. 5.15.</note>? what? in diſtreſſe (with <hi>Ahaz) yet more and more</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">2. Chron. 28.22.</note> 
               <hi>treſpaſſe and treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe against him? well might one ſay oh vnhappy perſons, whom ſtripes mol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifie not</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">Sult. in Iſ. c. <hi>1.</hi> p. <hi>33.</hi> In felices autem qui nec vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beribus mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſcunt.</note>. Well may I ſay; Not hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py they whom troubles mooue not to lay open their ſinnes, in the ſight of the Almightie.<note n="*" place="margin">Vſe 2. Exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to bee toucht, for to make confeſſion of ſinne in time of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction.</note> Farre oh farre be it from Vs (Beloued) to be
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:15204:14"/> ſo ſtupid. Perſonall afflictions vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſome of vs: Generall vpon moſt of vs: The ſtreame of our coyne we complaine runnes low, our corne growes deare, markets bad, the earth denies her foizon vnto vs, &amp; more eminent plagues then theſe (by all probabilities) are imminent ouer vs, and like to vexe vs, and ſhall none of theſe, not all of theſe worke vpon vs, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile with vs, to confeſſe to God what is the cauſe of theſe tragicall prologues, theſe beginning of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes? prouoke we our ſelues to this duty? learne wee as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet aduiſeth vs, <hi>to take words vnto our ſelues</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">Hoſ. 14.2.</note>, and ſay, <hi>Lord wee haue ſinned against thee, and fallen from thee by our iniquitie.</hi> Oh let not <hi>Pharaoh</hi> riſe vp in iudgement a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs: Propound we the pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne of theſe brethren my text ſpeakes off, vnto our ſelues. As
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:15204:15"/> diſtreſſe mooued them, ſo let di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe mooue vs to acknowledge, how diſhonourably we haue dealt with the Lord, how iniuriouſly with our brethren, how ſtrangely wee haue neglected the day and meanes of ſaluation, how ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly we haue affected the way and meanes of damnation. When we taſte of the bitterneſſe and ſharpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the fruite, looke we to the bitter tree whereon it growes with watry eyes, and ſorrowfull ſpirits; Mourne not ſo much for the croſſe, as the cauſe of it: talke not ſo much of the trouble, as the ground of it, which are thy ſinnes and thy tranſgreſſions. If afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons worke not vpon thy conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to make thee contrite, in ſoule, and willing to confeſſe thy ſinnes to God? what will: whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer therefore the diſtreſſe be, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for the quality, degree or time
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:15204:15"/> of it that thou lyeſt vnder, make but this wholeſome vſe of it to thy ſoule, at length to mourne for thy ſinnes at laſt, to acknowledge thy abhominations without any more adoe, let a word preuaile with thee, and the Lord bleſſe it that it may. As mans neceſſity is Gods oportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to ſhew mercy: So thy aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie, is thy opportunitie, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe thine iniquity and deplore thy miſery, which if thou doeſt neglect, what knoweſt thou whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther euer thou ſhalt haue the like call, the like occaſion againe. Wherefore I trow it is beſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling a mans ſelfe, when he is beſt fitted for it, and neuer fitter is hee, then in time of aduerſitie.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>3</label> Thirdly, hence we ſee one rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, why the Lord afflicts his owne children, it workes contrition in them, it workes confeſſion from them, two things wherewith the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:15204:16"/> Lord is greatly delighted. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when yee ſee Chriſtians bare and needy, and to want thoſe things which others haue in great abundance otherwiſe viſited, ceaſe to marueile at it, the Lord loues to haue their conſciences kept wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, and their tongue kept wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king againſt their owne ſinnes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him; and he knowes proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie to be a great entrance to ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of theſe, and very dangerous to lull conſcience, and tye vp the tongue, and therefore hee giues them a <hi>Michaiahs portion, feedes them with</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">1. King. 22.27.</note> 
               <hi>bread of affliction, and water of aduerſitie:</hi> and bleſſed be God that by any dealing of his (how tedious ſoeuer to the fleſh) they may be kept with remorſefull hearts, and ready tongues to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge their daily infirmities before his Maieſtie.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>4</label> Fourthly, doe afflictions worke
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:15204:16"/> vpon the conſcience, and produce confeſſion, euen ſometimes in the wicked themſelues, then we may ſee that the Lord will haue glory from the wicked, he can make an <hi>Ahab,</hi> a <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> &amp;c. to giue vnto him the praiſe of his owne iuſtice, and to confeſſe that he is righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and they wicked, and that there is no iniuſtice in him, deale he neuer ſo rigorouſly with them.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>5</label> Laſtly, this point ought to be of vſe to arme vs, againſt murmuring in the time of affliction, and to teach vs with all patience to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergoe thoſe troubles, which the Lord in his wiſedome doth lay vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vs. Shall wee grudge at that which may bring ſuch gaine vnto the ſoule? which (by Gods bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing) may be of vſe to awake our drowſie conſciences, and ſtirre our lame tongues to that confeſſion which<note n="r" place="margin">Beat Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nan. in Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tull <hi>469.</hi> Magistram virtutis du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem ſaluta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris itineris.</note> one calles the <hi>miſtreſſe of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:15204:17"/> vertue, a guide in the way to felicity,</hi> without which (as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth) a man cannot finde mercie at the hands of God? God forbid we ſhould be impatient for this, fall out with Gods prouidence for this<note n="ſ" place="margin">In quo igi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur ſapiens &amp; bonus vir à malis, &amp; in ſipien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus differt, viſi quod habet invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctam Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entiam qua ſtulti carent. Lactan. De vero cultu. lib. <hi>6.</hi> ca. <hi>18.</hi>
               </note>. Wherein I pray, doth a wiſe and good man differ from wicked men and fooles, but onely in this, <hi>that hee hath that patience which a foole wants. We finde</hi> (in Scripture) <hi>that the Patriarchs, Prophets, and all the iuſt ones, which were types and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures of Chriſt, did keepe nothing more to the praiſe of their vertues, then this, they had learned patience</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">Cypr. de bono patien. fol. <hi>105.</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenimus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nique &amp; patri ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chas, &amp;c.</note>. As, therefore <hi>(beloued)</hi> we pray, <hi>thy will be done,</hi> ſo let vs reſolue, we will patiently ſubmit vnto it, knowing that if we poſſeſſe our ſoules in pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, much good will redound vnto vs.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>2</label> 
               <note place="margin">An euill conſcience is an accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer.</note>I leaue the firſt point, and come vnto the ſecond. <hi>That an euill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:15204:17"/> hath an accuſing office.</hi> This truth hath its ground thus. Theſe ten ſonnes of <hi>Iacob</hi> had an euill conſcience, guiltie of wrong done to their brother <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> and now (vpon occaſion of ſome diſtreſſe) it accuſeth them, it articleth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them. What meaneth the trembling of <hi>Adam</hi> at Gods voice in the garden after hee had eaten the forbidden fruite<note n="u" place="margin">Gen. 3.10</note>? What meant the quaking of <hi>Foelix</hi> at <hi>Paules</hi> Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon of <hi>Temperance and iuſtice, and the iudgement to come</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Act. 24.16.</note>, after he had beene incontinent with <hi>Oruſilla,</hi> and plaide the tyrant ouer his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects<note n="x" place="margin">Gualt. in Act. Hom. <hi>105.</hi> p. <hi>265. 266.</hi>
               </note>? What meaneth the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexitie of <hi>Herod Aſcalonites,</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">So <hi>Euſeb.</hi> calles him. <hi>Eccleſ. Hiſt. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 7.</note> after he heard of the birth of Chriſt, who (as he thought) was like to put him beſide his throne? what meanes the feare which <hi>Herod</hi> the foxe had, that <hi>Iohn</hi> the Baptiſt was riſen from the dead, after he had
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:15204:18"/> vniuſtly taken his head away from him<note n="z" place="margin">Mark. 6.16.</note>? what meane (I ſay) all theſe, and the like examples if it were not the property, of an ill conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to accuſe a man of the ſinnes that he committeth. Hence it is that <hi>Eliphaz</hi> ſaith to <hi>Iob. The wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked man feareth all his daies, the ſound of trembling is alwaies in his eares</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Iob. 15.20.</note>. And doth not the Apoſtle ſpeake of an accuſing property which the conſcience hath, in the ſecond chapter of the Romanes at the 15. verſe?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>
               </label> And the ground of this do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine I take to be laide downe in the beginning of that verſe, where it is ſaid that euen the Gentiles haue the worke of the Law writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in their hearts.</p>
            <p>Now of the Law, there is a two-fold worke) (as<note n="b" place="margin">In Epiſt. ad Rom. p. <hi>227. 228.</hi> Legis duplex eſt opus, Impletiones, Notitiae.</note> 
               <hi>Brentius</hi> obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth,) The worke of fulfilling it, the worke of knowledge, the latter
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:15204:18"/> of which two the Apoſtle mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth in that place. Now this worke of knowledge, is to diſtinguiſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt good and bad, things honeſt and diſhoneſt, which worke euen the wickedeſt haue by nature in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grauen in their hearts: for in ſome meaſure they know what is honeſt and to be done, what is diſhoneſt and not to be done, when they then ſhall leaue that which they know they muſt doe, and perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trate that which they know they muſt not doe, muſt not their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience needes accuſe them, and condemne them?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
               </label> Peraduenture againſt this truth ſome will obiect the experience of our times, that we ſee for the moſt part, the lewdeſt and vngodlieſt perſons haue the leaſt heart-ſmart, the moſt quiet. Therefore, an euill conſcience is not in all, an accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing conſcience. Vnto which I
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:15204:19"/> anſwer: <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>1</label> firſt, with <hi>Bernards</hi> diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Cited by</hi> Hemingius Syntag. <hi>161 162.</hi> Mala &amp; tranquilla, mala &amp; tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bata.</note> that there is a two fold euill conſcience
<list>
                  <item>Quiet, and</item>
                  <item>Vnquiet.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>An euill conſcience and vnquiet, is without all queſtion of an accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing nature: none denies it. As for an euill conſcience and quiet, that is, when a man is ſwallowed vp in the depth of ſinne, that hee doth not ſo much, as entertaine one thing about repentance, but blind-folded is lead from one wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe to another: and them that haue ſuch a conſcience, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle calles<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>past feeling,</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Eph. 4.19.</note> yet ſuch as haue loſt all iudgement, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punction of heart, giuen ouer to a reprobate ſence. Now this kinde of euill conſcience, though it doth not alwaies execute the acts of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſing, yet ſtill it hath the habite, the quality of accuſing: and when
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:15204:19"/> it comes to be awakened, it will not onely accuſe, but alſo torment moſt grieuouſly, moſt intollerably. And as for thoſe that haue ſuch a conſcience, they cannot be ſaid to be quiet, or at peace properly (as you take peace for the tranquility of the minde) but rather to be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure, ſeared, obdurate and harde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: then which nothing can be worſe, nothing more miſerable. So then when we ſee the wickedeſt li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, to haue (as the word dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, the merrieſt liues; it is not from peace of conſcience, but from a ſeared conſcience, it is not becauſe their conſcience hath no accuſing power, but becauſe it doth not alwaies execute its accuſing office, for it neuer wants matter to accuſe. * For beſides, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> though wee ſee ſuch to liue quietly, and (to our thinking) to be at peace, yet ſecret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they may haue a ſting within
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:15204:20"/> them, which doth vexe, and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt them moſt grieuouſly, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that <hi>Salomons</hi> ſaying may be verified of them: in the middeſt of laughter, the heart is heauy.</p>
            <p>Before I come to the vſe: I muſt anſwer a queſtion. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
               </label> And this it is, Whither an accuſing conſcience be alwaies an euill conſcience? <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> To which I muſt giue ſatisfaction by diſtinguiſhing of the accuſing power of the conſcience: And that is to be conſidered in a two-fold reſpect: firſt, in regard of the ground of accuſing: ſecondly, in regard of the conſequents of it.</p>
            <p>Firſt, for the ground: the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience doth accuſe either vpon a good ground or a falſe: vpon a good ground it accuſeth, when be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing informed truly, either by the light of nature, or the light of grace, of things to be done or left vndone, it telleth a man of his
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:15204:20"/> fault, in the neglect of the one, in the practiſe of the other, as for example: <hi>Dauid</hi> knew by the light of nature, that he ſhould doe to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, as he would they ſhould doe to him; and that as he would not haue any man wrong him, either in his wife or life; ſo no more ſhould hee wrong his brother in the ſame kinde: he knew alſo by the Law of God, that neither mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther nor adultery were to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, heere is the ground: Now vpon this ground his heart ſmites him, when <hi>Nathan</hi> comes to him, his conſcience telles him, that he, euen he had ſinned in wronging his brother, both in his life, and his wife: in committing murther againſt the one, adultery with the other. Thus did <hi>Ioſephs</hi> brethrens conſcience accuſe them heere, for doubtleſſe they had learned, that cruelty was not to be exerciſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:15204:21"/> a naturall brother, the word and nature had taught them this: and therefore after they had wron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged him, their conſcience accuſe them.</p>
            <p>Secondly, vpon a bad ground, the conſciencc accuſeth, when an erroneous principle is laid; as for a Maſſe-prieſt to bee accuſed and troubled in his minde, for negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting his Maſſe and Popiſh deuoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or a Lay-papiſt for peruſing the Scriptures, when as it is not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the word of God, either to neglect the one, or peruſe the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>Secondly, for the conſequents that doe follow the accuſing of the conſcience, they are theſe. Firſt, ſorrow for the offence accuſed of, whither it be omiſſiue or commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue, or for the puniſhment which the conſcience telles the delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent he is lyable vnto. Secondly,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:15204:21"/> feare either to commit the like of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence againe, or to vndergoe the puniſhment due for that tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. Thirdly, ſecuritie ariſing ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from the right appeaſement of the conſcience, or from the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe ſtopping of the checkes of conſcience. Now for the direct an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering of the queſtion out of theſe premiſes, this is that which I haue to ſay, that alwaies an accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing conſcience is not an euill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. And this I can make good out of the premiſed diſtinctions. That conſcience that accuſeth vpon a good ground, and telles the offender, hee hath directly tranſgreſſed the Law of God, and withall produceth the beſt of theſe conſequent effects before ſpoken off. That conſcience which ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth vp feare to fall into the like ſinne againe, that worketh godly ſorrow for the ſinne committed,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:15204:22"/> that breedeth ſecurity in aſſurance of reconciliation: that conſcience, though it accuſeth, yet cannot properly be termed euill, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tender, and full of remorſe: on the contrary, if the conſcience bee terrified vpon Popiſh grounds, if after the accuſing office of the conſcience; yea, vpon a good ground alſo the partie ſorrowes more for the puniſhment deſerued, then the ſinne committed; if hee feareth rather the falling of the puniſhment vpon his head, then daſhing himſelfe againe vpon the rocke of the ſame or the like ſinne: And laſtly, if he groweth ſecure by ſtopping the mouth, and negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting the checkes of conſcience, theſe are true ſignes that the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience is euill which accuſeth, but if otherwiſe the conſcience may poſſibly accuſe and yet not be euill nor vncleane. This I thought
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:15204:22"/> good to anſwer it comming ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily in our way. I will deteine you no longer from the vſes which which are: For reproofe, comfort, terrour, and duty. The three for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer concerne ſome, with ſome dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference definitely, the latter re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects all without difference inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> Firſt (I ſay) heere is a ground of reproofe vnto thoſe, who haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies matter, and nothing elſe but matter of accuſation againſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, within themſelues; and yet they will ſtand vpon it, that they haue good conſciences; one hath matter of accuſation within him for his ryot, another for luſt, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for vſury, for bribery, for op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, for other wrongs done to his neighbour, another for bearing malice, another for lying, falſe wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe bearing, priuie ſlandering, horrible cruelty, ſhop-theeuery,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:15204:23"/> whoſe conſciences can tell them, that thus and thus, they deceiued ſuch and ſuch, ſo and ſo they haue deceiued others, at ſuch a time they committed ſuch a villany: in ſuch a place, ſuch impiety: heere they wrought filthineſſe, there vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſſe, &amp;c. neither were they ſo much as euer mooued for this ſinne, they neuer relented for it, neuer repented of it, and yet (I ſay) they are of opinion (and will not be beaten from it) that they haue good and very good conſciences; when as alas: how can it be, this being true that an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill conſcience, is an accuſing conſcience, and ſo on the other ſide, an accuſing conſcience, for the moſt part an euill conſcience. What doeſt thou man talke of a good conſcience, when it is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies like the troubled waters ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting vp dirt and filthineſſe in thine
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:15204:23"/> owne face; when as it is continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ringing a peale of thine abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations in thy eares? thou a good conſcience; when thou ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, lyeſt, cheateſt, playeſt the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mercifull, incontinent, intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate beaſt, ſlandereſt thy neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour; ſitteſt and ſpeakeſt againſt thine owne mothers ſonne, brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt Gods Sabbaths, deſpiſeſt Gods ordinances: It goes againſt thy conſcience (as thou rudely profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt) to regard a Preacher, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect a profeſſor, or walke accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to an holy profeſſion; thou a good conſcience I ſay? No no; If indeede, (thy conſcience ſmiting thee vpon good ground) thou wert but drawne to heartie ſorrow for thy offences, to an holy feare not to commit them againe, it were ſomething; then thou mighteſt be beleeued, when thou boaſteſt of thy ſelfe as free from an euill
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:15204:24"/> conſcience? but otherwiſe, thou art to be reprooued for vaine-glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious bragging. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
               </label> But I thanke God I am at quiet in my conſcience? <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> Art thou ſo, and yet liueſt in thy ſinnes? ſo much the more feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full is thy condition; no iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to a reprobate ſenſe; Oh to be paſt feeling, this is moſt pitti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. Sayeſt thou, thou art at quiet? nay thou deceiueſt thy ſelfe, thy conſcience is ſeared; neither is thy quiet from hence, becauſe thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience hath no crime, to lay to thy charge, but becauſe thou wilt not heare thy conſcience ſpeake when it doth accuſe thee. It may be, becauſe thou wouldeſt make men beleeue thou art not guiltie of thoſe euils, which happily at ſome times thou art ſtung for within thy ſelfe, therefore thou ſetteſt a good face vpon the matter (as ſome that lye a dying, ſay they
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:15204:24"/> feare not death) when as indeede they feare nothing more: Or put caſe thou ſayeſt true (as I ſaid) when thou affirmeſt, thy minde is not crazed: the more horror re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth for thee againſt the time of thine awaking; inſomuch, that as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaid, he ſhould be ſatisfied with the light of Gods counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance ſhining vpon him after his riſing, thou art like on the other ſide to be terrified with the goades of thine owne conſcience ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king againſt thee, at the time of thy rowſing, vnleſſe the Lord bee the more gracious vnto thee. I conclude therefore, it is a great folly (moſt worthy of reproofe) in thee, to thinke thou haſt not an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill conſcience, when thy conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation is vncleane, abounding with noyſome euils, as matter of iuſt accuſation againſt thee.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> Secondly, heere is comfort to
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:15204:25"/> thoſe that haue good conſciences; their happineſſe is vnſpeakeable, their condition moſt peaceable; for if ſo be an euill conſcience bee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies of an accuſing qualitie, then their good conſcience is alwaies of an excuſing property. Excuſing property (I ſay) or quality, for I denie not but a good conſcience may and doth exerciſe many a time accuſing actions. The heart of <hi>Dauid</hi> may ſmite him, for taking away <hi>Vriahs</hi> life, for defiling <hi>Vri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ahs</hi> wife<note n="e" place="margin">2. Sam. 12.13.</note> for cutting off the lap of <hi>Sauls</hi> garment<note n="f" place="margin">1. Sam. 24.4.</note>, for numbring his people contrary to Gods com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement<note n="g" place="margin">2. Sam. 24</note>, I know <hi>Peters</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience did article againſt him, for denying and forſwearing his Lord and Maſter<note n="h" place="margin">Math. 26.75.</note>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and there is neuer a Chriſtian but can witneſſe with mee, that his owne conſcience tels him daily of his daily faylings; yet I ſay, his conſcience is not an habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:15204:25"/> accuſer, as to doe nothing elſe but accuſe him, or as though it had nothing elſe in it ſelfe, but iuſt matter of accuſation againſt him: this (I ſay) he is freed from, which an euill man is not. And rather it hath an accuſing power: now for a mans conſcience to haue an excuſing habite and quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, what a ſweete and comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thing is it? What? free from the terrours of a tormenting ſoule? free from the wounds of ſpirit, which mortall ſtrength cannot beare? what man can but admire this? what heart will not exalt and reioyce to feele this? <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
               </label> Oh but I am tormented, I am terrified will (the poore Chriſtian ſay,)<note n="*" place="margin">For in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede of all others, they are moſt troubled.</note> I cannot be ſo at peace in my ſelfe, as I faine would be, my conſcience is euer and anone about my eares? <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> Very like, if it bee tender, it cannot chooſe but ſo it muſt bee. Perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:15204:26"/> thou haſt not yet attained vnto that ſpirit of adoption, to witneſſe to thy ſpirit in that full meaſure that thou art the childe of God, happily thou art but yet in the way to attaine vnto it. It may be thou woundeſt thy conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, by beeing ſomething too ventrous vpon that which thou haſt no warrant for, If it be ſo; then I doe not much meruaile that thou canſt not haue that quiet thou doeſt deſire; and well will it proue for thee at the laſt, that thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience doth ſo ſmite thee. But what of this? haſt thou no cauſe therefore to reioyce in the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of thy conſcience? Thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience accuſeth thee vpon a good ground, doth it? thou feareſt the ſinne more then the puniſhment, thou ſorroweſt for the offence done, more then for the ſcourge due, doeſt thou not? thou art wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:15204:26"/> to heare thy conſcience ſpeak, and thou ſayeſt? <hi>Conſcience doe thine office, by the grace of God I will not checke thee, nor ſtoppe vp mine eares againſt thee;</hi> thou art carefull to haue thy conſcience pacified by the right meane, euen by the aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance that through Chriſt his blood, thou art purged from the ſinne which thy conſcience ſmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth thee for, art thou not? If yea; then know thou to thy comfort, that though thy conſcience (when there is reaſon for it) doth execute ſome accuſing acts againſt thee, yet habitually it will prooue to bee an excuſer of thee. Wherefore doe not thou by this cauill cheate thy ſelfe of the comfort that belongs vnto thee. If thy conſcience be at ods with thee vpon ſome good ground, giue all diligence to get it appeaſed with the aſſurance of Gods loue, and caſt not downe thy
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:15204:27"/> ſelfe out of meaſure, as if thy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence had nothing elſe but matter to accuſe thee off. And to encreaſe thy comfort vpon this ground, meditate thou of the benefits of an excuſing conſcience: as name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>The bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits of an excuſing conſcience.</hi> Quaenam ſumma boni? meus quae ſibi conſcia recti, Auſon.</note> firſt an excuſing conſcience will anſwer and out-weigh all the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſations for ſinne, and ſuch and ſuch acts of ſin as can be brought in to moleſt the ſoule, for ſuch a conſcience is purified by the blood of Chriſt, freed from the guilt of ſinne, hath to obiect Chriſts me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits againſt its owne de-merits, the obiecting of which vpon good ground, will anſwer all the ſpitefull cauils of the malicious tempter. Secondly,<note place="margin">2. Benefi.</note> an excuſing conſcience will be a rocke of comfort in the time of diſtreſſe, when thou lyeſt vpon thy ſicke bed it will accheere thee, as <hi>Ezekiah</hi> did, when he ſaid,<note n="i" place="margin">Iſa. 38.3.</note> 
               <hi>Lord remember how I haue walked
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:15204:27"/> before thee in truth, with a perfect heart, &amp;c.</hi> When the world takes her wings and flyes away from thee, when thy earthly friends for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake thee, and diſpute againſt thee, and all humane helpes faile thee, this will be a cordiall and conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion vnto thee.<note place="margin">3. Benefi.</note> And which is laſt of all, and yet beſt of all, it will goe with thee to the iudgement ſeate of Chriſt, defie the deuill to his face, acquit thee and abſolue thee of all the crimes which euer thou wert, either iuſtly by the accuſing acts of it, or vniuſtly by the ſpite of Satan and his wicked inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments charged withall. Loe this is the good, the gaine heere; heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, that an excuſing conſcience doth and will bring thee; and yet thy good conſcience hath this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſing quality. Why art thou then ſo deiected thou Chriſtian, and why is thy ſoule ſo ſad within thee;
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:15204:28"/> the Lord comfort thee vpon this ground, the Lord (with this) ſpeak peaceably vnto thy ſoule.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>3</label> Thirdly, heere is terrour vnto thee that haſt an euill conſcience, knoweſt thou man what it is? if thou beeſt ignorant, heare the point in hand telling thee what it is an accuſing conſcience. And though peraduenture thou maieſt be ſecure, haue it lie a ſleepe a long time together,<note n="l" place="margin">Mat. 27.5.</note> yet like a maſtiffe curre at laſt it will awake and be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout thy eares; and when it awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, who can ſtoppe the voyce, who can allay the fury of it? thy witte cannot doe it, take <hi>Achi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tophel</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">2. Sam. 17</note> for witneſſe; Thy wealth cannot doe it, take <hi>Iudas</hi> for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample. Thy authority can not do it, take <hi>Iulian</hi> for thy proofe. Thy<note n="*" place="margin">Neque ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus volup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet, neque a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micorum colloquia ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem refocilla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, vel libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rare, ab vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gente anxie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate poſſunt. Chryſoſt. in Gen. hom. <hi>19.</hi>
               </note> ſweete bitte and iouiall compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie cannot doe it, take<note n="n" place="margin">Dan. 5. <hi>Obiect.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Balſhazzar</hi> for warrant. But what if my conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:15204:28"/> doth accuſe mee? what of that? is it any great matter? Thou ſhalt know that when thou tryeſt it. And in the meane time (for what I can anſwer thee in this im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent demand) this I ſay to thee. To haue an accuſing conſcience, habitually is not onely to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued of the ſweete benefits of an excuſing conſcience, which I ſpake off in the former vſe, but alſo in ſtead of them, to meete with the contrary inconueniences. Firſt, thine accuſing conſcience will out-weigh all the good deeds that euer thou haſt done, thy prayers, almes, temperate, ciuill, neighbour-like carriage and behauiour, and the like: It ſhall little auaile thee to alleadge any of theſe things to thy comfort, when thy euill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience is vp in armes againſt thee;<note place="margin">A ſimile.</note> Let a man be iuſtly accuſed at ſome temporall barre for rape, inceſt,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:15204:29"/> murthering of the innocent, or any fellony that deſerues death, what will it boote him to pleade his gentility, his hoſpitality, and that he hath beene a good friend to the common-wealth, &amp;c. if ſo be his accuſer comes in ſtrongly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, and reſolues to proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute him to the very death? Alas, what would it haue aduantaged <hi>Iudas</hi> to haue alleadged his prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, his doing of miracles, his ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting out of deuils: <hi>Achitophel</hi> his policy, &amp; prouidence for the State &amp; common-wealth, when as their euil co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſciences did torment them, the one for betraying his innocent Maſter, the other for plotting trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon againſt his lawfull Soueraigne? I tell thee when conſcience is a do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing its accuſing office, it will nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther heare of thy honeſty, nor ciui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, nor liberalitie, nor any thing elſe good in it ſelfe, that hath been
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:15204:29"/> done by thee for corrupt ends, but it will take them all, as if they had neuer beene done: yea accuſe thee for failing in the manner.</p>
            <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">Conſcientia mala bene ſperare non poteſt. Aug. in Pſal. <hi>31.</hi>
               </note> it will deny thee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in time of diſtreſſe: when thy body is tormented with corporall diſeaſes, and thou lye toſſing and tumbling from one ſide of the bed to the other, and faine wouldeſt haue eaſe. When thy corne, cattell, ſubſtance, goods are taken away from thee and thou brought to pouertie, when ſcarcitie pincheth thee, when friends leaue thee, and enemies ſet againſt thee, to haue content and quiet within, it were ſome comfort, but (oh miſerable perſon) that is not to be had, thy conſcience is buffeting thee, and vexing thee within, dealing with thee as the conſciences of theſe brethren, with them ſuggeſting matter of terrour vnto them in the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:15204:30"/> time of their outward extreami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy accuſing co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce comes at the bar with thee after this life, it will be a co-partner with that<note n="*" place="margin">Apoc. 12.10.</note> accuſer of the brethren Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan againſt thee, to the vtter ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw, and euerlaſting confuſion. Now go to thou ſeared ſinner, thou ſtiffe-necked offender, aske in ſcof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fing wiſe, what matter it is if thy conſcience doe accuſe thee. Loe, thou ſeeſt what a matter it is; And were it not that I wanted a tongue to expreſſe, and then an eye to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, an heart to conſider the fearefulneſſe of thy condition, it could not chooſe but be like the ſight of the figures that <hi>Balſhazzar</hi> ſaw vpon the wall, or elſe like the ſound of the Sermon that the Iewes heard Saint <hi>Peter</hi> preach<note n="o" place="margin">Act. 2.</note>, euen an occaſion to make thy loynes ſhake and thy ioynts trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:15204:30"/> thy heart ſoft, and thy ſoule humble, what? no comfort to be reaped by thee, in the beſt actions thou performeſt? In likelihood to be left like a deſolate forlorne and comfortleſſe creature in the time of diſtreſſe? in ieopardie to haue the ſting of conſcience per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing of thee to Gods iudgement barre, the worme of conſcience, gnawing on thee, for euermore after thy few and euill dayes be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded? what can be more terrible, more woefull? Verily, if the thought of theſe things preuaile not to humble thee, theſe terrours are as like to ouertake thee as death it ſelfe, then which nothing is more ſure, more certaine. The Lord therefore mooue thy heart with this, if it bee his holy will. Amen.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>4</label> Laſtly, heere is indefinite exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to all without difference,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:15204:31"/> that they would giue all diligence both to attaine and reteine conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences that are good, both to bee freed of and preſerued from con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences that are euill. The exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of this two-fold duty, tooke vp a great deale of Saint <hi>Paules</hi> care, as appeareth in ſundry pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtations (of his diligence in this kinde) in the ſeuerall Epiſtles which he writeth vnto the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. Now if the worthy example of that worthy Apoſtle be to bee followed by vs in any thing that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer he did, it is to be imitated and followed in this; and that ſo much the rather, becauſe of the ground to perſwade to, and the motiue to enforce the duty, which the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine in hand affordeth; telling vs that an <hi>euill conſcience is</hi> an accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, a vexing, a tormenting conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. Now tell mee who would be willing to bee peſtered with a
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:15204:31"/> tormenting conſcience? who takes any pleaſure to haue the darts of the Almighty dagging at the heart; or the arrowes of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie drinking vp of the ſpirit? Quiet of ſoule and tranquillity of minde is that that All doe natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſire. The vngodly themſelues wiſh for peace, and rather then they would be without it, they will content themſelues with a falſe peace, with carnall ſecuritie. And there is none that liueth vnto whom terrours and tortures inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall and inward are not tedious and irkeſome, would we then be freed and preſerued from ſuch ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, ſuch wounds, ſuch daggers? would we haue true peace, and ſound tranquilitie indeede? then let (as I ſaide) endeauour to get good conſciences if we want them, &amp; to keepe them if we haue them, or when we ſhal attaine vnto them.</p>
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:15204:32"/>
            <p>And for better furtherance in ſo weighty a duty as this is, I will commend to Gods bleſſing and thine vſe, two rankes or ſorts of rules. In the firſt whereof I will preſcribe remedies to cure the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lady of an euill conſcience, or ſet downe meanes to bring thee to a good conſcience. In the ſecond I will preſcribe antidotes to keepe thee from falling into the ſame diſeaſe of an euill conſcience a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, or acquaint thee with helps to keepe thy conſcience ſound and good if it bee ſo already. In both of which before thou goeſt any further, I deſire at thy hands a reſolution to vſe both, ſo neither I in writing this, nor thou in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſhall looſe our labour.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Remedies to cure an euill, or meanes to get a good conſcience.</note>For the firſt, I minde to lay a ground out of which to draw the rules, or ſome of the rules at leaſt, and that ground ſhall be the defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:15204:32"/> or deſcription of a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience and a bad.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>Piſca. in</hi> 1. Tim. 1. Obſ. 24. What a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience is.</note>Some define a good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence thus.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A good conſcience, is the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our minde approouing that which we doe, as pleaſing to good, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that we our ſelues pleaſe God through Chriſt, and becauſe we ſtudy to pleaſe him, with a ſerious purpoſe of walking according to his will.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Others more briefely thus.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A good conſcience, is a ioy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heming. Syntag. <hi>161.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ſprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging out of the remembrance of a life holily and honeſtly led, or a confidence of ſinne remitted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for a <hi>bad conſcience, I take it to be contrary to the good,</hi> and may bee defined either, firſt thus.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A bad conſcience is the cenſure of the minde,</hi>
               <note place="margin">What a bad conſcience is.</note> 
               <hi>diſallowing that which we doe as diſpleaſing to God, inſomuch as neither our perſons doe pleaſe him through Chriſt, nor (as our conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:15204:33"/> tell vs) we ſtudie to pleaſe him in our liues with a ſtedfaſt purpoſe of heart to conforme vnto his will.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Or ſecondly thus: <hi>An euill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, is a trembling and feare ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing out of the remembrance of a life lewdly &amp; wickedly led.</hi> This ground by theſe deſcriptions thus laide, I draw out theſe directions, for the <hi>getting of a good, and ridding of an euill conſcience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1. Remedy of an euill conſcience.</note>The firſt is the ſpirit of diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, a iudgement to diſcerne of things that differ. For it is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite that a good conſcience ſhould be informed vpon a good ground, true principles, now how can that be, except a man hath iudgement to try and diſcerne the ground, whither it be ſound or falſe? It is the office of conſcience, either to allow or diſallow, but how can it allow of what is good, or diſallow that which is euill, except the party
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:15204:33"/> hath knowledge both of good and euil, that is, what is good, and what is euill. A right vnderſtanding heart, and a good conſcience; a blinde minde, and a bad conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; are ordinarily yoaked toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. If Papiſts did not make ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance the mother of deuotion. If our generation of vnwiſe and carnall ones did not like to liue in blindneſſe of heart without ſauing knowledge, both the one and the other would haue better conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences then they haue. My counſell therefore to thee, is this, to get thoſe chaines of darkenes where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withall thy heart is fettered, pulled off, and thoſe miſts of ignorance, with which thy vnderſtanding is darkened remooued away, that thou maieſt be able to diſcerne of things that differ, that ſo the right information of thy minde, may prooue to be a meane of the ſound
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:15204:34"/> reformation of thy conſcience, and ſo that goodneſſe may be reſtored to it, which by nature thou art quite bereaued and depriued off.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. Remedy.</note>Secondly, when thou haſt attai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnto a ſound iudgement, and canſt put a difference betwixt good and euill, then it ſhall bee good for thee to approoue of, the one to diſallow the other. For when men againſt the light of their own knowledge, ſhal like <hi>Iulian</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">Socr. hiſt. lib. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> &amp; <hi>Ecebolius</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Id ibid. c. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> diſallow of that which is good, and like the Scribes and Phariſees approoue of that which is euill, is it poſſible for them, ſo long as they ſo remaine, to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medied and cured of their euill conſciences?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Paul</hi> praies on the behalfe of the brethren at <hi>Philippi,</hi> that <hi>they might approoue of things that are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Phil. 1.10.</note>, which prayer hee would haue neuer made, had not he ſeene
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:15204:34"/> it, a matter very vſefull and need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full againſt an euill, and for a good and honeſt conſcience, to approue of things honeſt according to the excellency of the ſame: Wee ſee men and women, to diſlike of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of Sermons in publike aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, of offering vp ſacrifice in their priuate families, of making profeſſion of religion; and they like better of beeing preſent at ſtage-playes, the very theaters of luſt:<note n="t" place="margin">
                  <hi>For ſo</hi> Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian <hi>cals it.</hi> lib. de Spectaculis. <hi>694.</hi> Thea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trum vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris.</note> 
               <hi>Of ryoting in Tauernes,</hi> and tap-houſes, being (as they are abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed) <hi>the very ſchooles of the deuill:</hi> they approoue better of allowing inordinate courſes. And hence it comes to paſſe that their conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences are ſo vile and euill as they are. Deale plainly with me now, doeſt thou in good earneſt deſire a good conſcience; like of that which is good, as moſt worthy to be loued, diſlike of that which is
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:15204:35"/> euill, as moſt worthy to be hated, and in time thou ſhall finde thy loue ſo ſtrongly inflamed towards the one; thy hatred ſo ſoundly ſharpened againſt the other; that thy conſcience ſhall be cleere be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, and honeſt towards men.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">3. Remedy.</note>Thirdly, hearken to the chekes of conſcience; be willing to heare conſcience ſpeake, and to take a carefull view of thoſe articles, which it preſenteth vnto thee, and bringeth in againſt thee.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Seneca E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. lib. <hi>1.</hi> Epiſtola <hi>43.</hi> ad calcem. O te miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſi con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temnis hunc teſtem.</note>
               <hi>O miſerable man that thou art,</hi> (could the heathen ſay) <hi>if thou con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temneſt this witneſſe.</hi> When thy conſcience ſets vpon thee, as <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than</hi> did vpon <hi>Dauid, thou art the man;</hi> or <hi>thou art the woman</hi> that haſt failed in this duty, fallen into this iniquity, omitted that good, committed that euill; thinke in thy heart it is verily true, and ſay in
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:15204:35"/> thy ſelfe, as <hi>Dauid</hi> to <hi>Nathan: I haue ſinned.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the fourth place,<note place="margin">4. Remedy.</note> ſorrow thou after a godly manner, for thoſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils which thy conſcience (being rightly informed) chargeth thee withall; imitate Saint <hi>Peters</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerts; who no ſooner were accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in their conſciences by occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his Sermon, of that crime of crucifying Chriſt, but they were pricked, touched with remorſe and ſorrow for the ſame. Oh if as of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten as thy conſcience ſmites thee, thou hadſt but the grace with <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraim</hi> to ſmite thy thigh and ſay,<note place="margin">5. Remedy.</note> what haue I done, thou wouldſt grow to haue a great deale better conſcience then thou haſt.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, Faith is helpefull and neceſſary in this worke: <hi>For he that is wholly diſeaſed with vnbeleefe</hi> (ſaith one<note n="u" place="margin">Iodoch. Willich. in <hi>1. Tim. 1.19.</hi> Qui in fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litatis mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo laborat, huius non poteſt eſſe bona conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entia.</note>) <hi>his conſcience cannot bee good.</hi> This is plainly intimated by
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:15204:36"/> Saint <hi>Paul</hi> to the Hebrewes, in a compariſon which there hee v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth<note n="*" place="margin">Heb. 9.13, 14.</note>. <hi>If the blood of Buls and Goates, and the aſhes of an Heifer, ſprinkling the vncleane, ſanctifieth to the purifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the fleſh: How much more ſhall the blood of Christ, who through the eternall Spirit offered himſelfe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſpot to God, purge your conſciences from dead workes to ſerue the liuing God?</hi> In which words by an ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie betwixt the type and the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titype, the Apoſtle prooueth the efficacy of Chriſts cleanſing; which cleanſing he calles the purifying of the conſcience from <hi>dead workes,</hi> yea from ſin which bringeth death, and is liued in, by men that are ſpiritually dead. Now if the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience cannot bee cleanſed from ſinne but by the blood of Chriſt, then it cannot become good, but by faith which apprehendeth the blood of Chriſt to our purging.
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:15204:36"/> And beſides, if ſo be a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience be, (as is expreſſed in the firſt definition<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> 66.</note>,) <hi>the iudgement of the minde, approouing of that which we doe as pleaſing to God, becauſe our perſons pleaſe God,</hi> or elſe (as is ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the ſecond definition) <hi>a confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of ſinne remitted,</hi> what doth this argue but a neceſſity of faith, to get a good conſcience, by which faith (as it apprehends the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe of Chriſt) both our <hi>perſons</hi> come to pleaſe God, and our ſoules are confident of the pardon of our ſinnes? Well then wouldſt thou be purged from an euill conſcience? doe this; when thy conſcience (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing rightly informed) hath accuſed thee as guilty of ſuch and ſuch ſinnes, and thou beeſt heartily ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and truly humbled for the ſame, get thee by faith to the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of Chriſts blood, bathe thee in it, ſeeke to haue thy conſcience
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:15204:37"/> appeaſed by the aſſurance of the pardon of thy ſinnes through Chriſt Ieſus alone, make this thy maine drift of giuing attendance vpon Gods ordinances, and thy e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill conſcience will be as effectual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cleanſed from thoſe euils that make it bee, as by the legall clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings in the ceremoniall law, fleſh was wont to be purged from lepro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, peſtilence, or any ſuch like fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy contagion.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">6. Remedie.</note>Laſtly, the ſtudy and practiſe of a godly life, breedeth and brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth a good conſcience; And this helpe the laſt clauſe in the firſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finition of a good conſcience af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fordeth, where is prooued that therefore a good conſcience doth approoue of what <hi>we doe</hi> as good, as <hi>well becauſe wee haue an earneſt ſtudie and ſerious purpoſe of walking according to Gods will,</hi> as becauſe <hi>we know our perſons pleaſing to God</hi>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:15204:37"/> through faith in Chriſt. And Saint <hi>Peter</hi> makes it good, in his firſt E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle third chapter, 15, and 16. verſes, where ſpeaking of a good conſcience, he ioynes withall, both a <hi>ſanctifying the Lord God in our hearts,</hi> that is, a ſtudy and ſerious purpoſe to ſerue him, and alſo a <hi>good conuerſation in Chriſt,</hi> to ſtop the mouthes of thoſe that are rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to accuſe vs as euill doers, that is a practiſe of the workes of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, giuing vs to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that it is impoſſible to haue a good conſcience, except we lead &amp; purpoſe &amp; ſtudy to lead a godly life.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the rules I thought good to lay downe for thy furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance in getting a good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; If hauing vſed the ſame heretofore thou haſt found it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, or by Gods bleſſing ſhalt obtaine it afterward; to the end thou mayeſt keepe it, marke a word
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:15204:38"/> or two more: and then I will bring thee out of this point, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I haue held thee longer then I thought at the firſt.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">How to keepe a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</note>And to this purpoſe, I will lay downe one generall caution, out of which I will draw the whole direction, and that is, it ſhall bee good for thee, to take heed of offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring any wrong or violence there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto:<note place="margin">Simile.</note> If it be as wee commonly vſe to ſay, it is great pitty to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force an entire friend to inconue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences againſt his will; it is much more pitty to enforce a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, (whereunto no earthly friend is comparable, both in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the good that it doth vs in the time of proſperitie, and the comfort it brings vs in the day of aduerſitie? Now the conſcience is enforced, or hath violence offered vnto it two waies, either when we would haue it more large then it
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:15204:38"/> ſhould be, or more ſtreight then it neede be.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the conſcience is made more large then it ſhould be, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming, or venturing further in the omiſſion of ſome duty, or in the giuing place to ſome infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, then there is warrant. Vnto which preſumption there are theſe fiue ſteppes or degrees.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Degree. </seg>1</label> Firſt, a ſecret wiſh that ſuch a thing might be done,<note place="margin">1. How the by-conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is made too large. Degrees to preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which tend to make the conſcience too large.</note> which wee know to bee vnlawfull, that ſuch a duty were not required, which we know to bee ſtrictly enioyned.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Degree. </seg>2</label> Secondly, vpon this wiſh an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtulation with our ſelues, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it may bee no way lawfull to commit that vice, to neglect that duty, ſo making that now queſtio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, which before we knew to be abſolute euery way vnlawfull.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Degree. </seg>3</label> Thirdly, a ſtrong imagination
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:15204:39"/> vpon this queſtion, that it may be very gainefull and commodious, if we doe take ſome liberty to our ſelues in this kinde.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Degree. </seg>4</label> The fourth degree, is to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound vnto our ſelues the infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Saints for our patterne, reaſoning thus, <hi>as good Chriſtians as I am, better men then I am, haue done thus and thus, haue neglected this and this, and therefore I may be bold without any great danger, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Degree. </seg>5</label> And the fift is a careleſſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, that if it bee but once or twice done, or ſeldome neglected, it cannot bee hurtfull, <hi>God is mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull, wee are in his fauour, his loue cannot alter,</hi> and I know not what. And ſo by conſequent from all this premiſes, a preſumptuous perpetrating of the offence. By theſe degrees, wee come to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume, and to ſtretch conſcience (to
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:15204:39"/> the wounding of it,) beyond its bounds, which is one kinde of enforcing of it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the <hi>Conſcience</hi> comes to bee ſtreightened three manner of wayes:<note place="margin">2. How the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is made too ſtreight.</note> firſt by ignorance in the nature of the obligation, and ſubiection of the conſcience<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, by yeelding vnto doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings: thirdly, by a kinde of tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porary deſpaire, either of Gods prouidence to releeue vs in our temporall wants and dangers, or of his readineſſe to accheere vs in our ſpirituall deſertions.</p>
            <p>That the firſt of theſe euils doth ſtreighten the conſcience, it is plaine by this argument. <hi>What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer doth cauſe ſcrupulous di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraction</hi> or <hi>diſtracting ſcruple, doth bring the conſcience into ſtreights.</hi> But <hi>ignorance in the nature of the binding and ſubiecting of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:15204:40"/> doth cauſe ſcrupulous diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. Therefore ſuch an ignorance ſtreightens the conſcience.</hi> For when the Chriſtian knows not through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly what things binde the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. Wherein <hi>conſcience</hi> is to be ſubiect, how farre forth things binde, nor how or in what caſes, with what conditions conſcience is to ſubmit, muſt it not needes bring him into a world of diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions? How can it otherwiſe bee?</p>
            <p>Secondly, that yeelding to doubtings, doe ſtraighten the conſcience, it is cleere, becauſe doubtings are enemies to the peace of the conſcience, which peace is the<note n="*" place="margin">Cordis de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectatio eſt cordis dila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatio. Auguſt.</note> conſciences ſweete enlargement. Vnto this peace al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo deſpaire of Gods prouidence, either ouer the outward man in the time of affliction, or ouer the
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:15204:40"/> ſoule, in the time of deſertion, is an aduerſary; therefore thirdly deſpaire muſt needs alſo diſtreſſe the conſcience.</p>
            <p>Well then, wouldſt thou keepe a good conſcience, as a continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all feaſt, obſerue in generall, two rules. Allow no larger bounds to thy conſcience, then with warrant thou maieſt by vaine preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Bring thy conſcience into no more thraldome and bondage then thou needeſt.</p>
            <p>To helpe thee in the firſt,<note place="margin">Subordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate helpes, to the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing of the firſt ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall rule.</note> that thou maieſt not preſume: marke theſe particulars.</p>
            <p>Firſt, doe not wiſh in thy heart any vnlawfull thing to bee law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, that thou might'ſt the ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier commit it, nor any neceſſary duty indifferent, that thou mightſt not be tyed vnto it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, if thou beeſt well in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:15204:41"/> of the vnlawfulneſſe of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny euill, of the neceſſitie of any duty, abiure the court of facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in thy conſcience, enquire not after a diſpenſation for thy ſelfe in ſpeciall, expoſtulate not whither thou mayeſt, or mayeſt not, commit it, or neglect it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Be not of conceite that neglect of any holy or neceſſary duty, or the committing of any ſinne can be gainefull and aduantageable to thy outward ſtate. For it is a ſilly gaine that is purchaſed with a wound to the ſpirit, and a cracke to the conſcience.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Set not the infirmities of belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers before thine eyes for imitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but for caution, not to embol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den thee, to doe as they did, but to make thee the more obſeruant of thine owne waies, leaſt that thou ſhouldeſt doe as they did. For
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:15204:41"/> euery fatte ſtands vpon its owne bottome; and little peace wilt thou haue to imitate any mortall man, in that which is offenſiue to thy God.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Conclude not that thou wilt but doe the deede once, or twice, or ſeldome; For ſinne is like a ſerpent, if it gets but in the head, it will get in the whole body, and it is a clinging and encroaching gueſt, whereof thou canſt not be ſo ſoone rid as thou liſteſt, after thou haſt giuen entertainment vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it: neither thinkeſt thou maieſt be the bolder, becauſe thou art in Gods fauour, which can neuer change nor alter: thou art not ſo ſure of heauen, but that the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill (though he cannot robbe thee of it) yet can make thee queſtion it to the perplexing of thy ſoule. Take heede (I ſay) that by theſe
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:15204:42"/> ſteps thou climbeſt not vp the lad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of preſumption, for then that there is no greater enemie, to an holy and blameleſſe life, the maintaining of which holy life, is the greateſt preſeruatiue to a good conſcience that can be.</p>
            <p>Secondly, as thus by preſuming, thou muſt not ſtretch thy conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.<note place="margin">Subordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate helpes to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall rule.</note> So to the end thou mayeſt not ſtreighten conſcience, thou muſt doe three things.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, get a ſound knowledge and right vnderſtanding of the binding, and ſubiection of the conſcience, to wit, whereby and how it is bound, wherein and how it is to be ſubiect.</p>
            <p>Now for thy better informati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in this, know that ſome things binde the conſcience immediately or properly;<note place="margin">What binds the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately <hi>viz.</hi> Law, Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell.</note> ſome things, mediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly or improperly. Firſt immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:15204:42"/> that doth binde the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, which hath moſt abſolute power and authoritie in it ſelfe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the conſcience, and thus the Law and Goſpell bindes the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience; or the word of God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended in the bookes of the Old and New Teſtament. Firſt, for the Law.</p>
            <p>That is three-fold, morall, iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciall, ceremoniall.<note place="margin">1. Law, and that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, iudici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The morall Law reſpecteth the duties of loue which wee owe to God and our neighbour, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed in the firſt and ſecond table, now to know how this binds con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,<note place="margin">1. How the morall Law bindes the conſcience.</note> theſe two rules muſt bee obſerued. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Rule. </seg>1</label> Firſt, <hi>That the ſecond ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble muſt giue place to the firſt, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that if two duties come in oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition one to the other, and the firſt ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble binds the conſcience to the one,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Two rules to ſhow how the morall law bindes the conſcience.</note> 
               <hi>the ſecond to the other, ſimply by it ſelfe,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:15204:43"/> that duty which is inioyned in the firſt, must be performed rather then that which is preſcribed in the ſecond.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The rule amplified.</note>To amplifie it. The ſecond ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble binds me to performe all teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of loue to my neighbour; the firſt to execute all offices of pietie towards God; Such and ſuch a teſtimony of loue to my neighbour, may in ſome caſe not ſtand with my piety towards God: in this caſe my conſcience muſt ſubmit it ſelfe, rather to the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of God, then pleaſing of man. Albeit, in ſome caſe we are to neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect ſome duties to God, that wee may releeue the preſent neceſſitie of our brother, which is warranted by that rule of Chriſt; I will haue mercy and not ſacrifice.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Rule. </seg>2</label> The ſecond rule is this; <hi>That the generall Law muſt giue way to the ſpeciall.</hi> Take an example, or two.
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:15204:43"/> 
               <hi>Thou ſhalt doe no murther:<note place="margin">The rule examplifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</note> Thou ſhalt not ſteale</hi> are generall lawes. <hi>Abraham take thy ſonne, thine onely ſonne Iſaac, and offer him vp in ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Gen. 22.22.</note>. <hi>Euery woman ſhall borrow of her neighbour, and of her that ſoiour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth in the houſe, iewels of ſiluer, and iewels of gold, and yee ſhall ſpoile the Egyptians</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">Exod. 3, 22.</note>, were ſpeciall comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements. Both of theſe, euen ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall and ſpeciall, doe binde the conſcience: In this caſe, which muſt <hi>Abraham</hi> and the Iſraelites chiefely ſubmit vnto? To the ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall; he muſt attempt to ſacrifice, his ſonne, notwithſtanding this, Thou ſhalt doe no murther. They muſt rob the Egyptians of their iewels and treaſures, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that precept; <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſteale.</hi> Why? becauſe the ſpeciall had at that time more power ouer the conſciences of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and the Iſraelites then the generall.</p>
            <pb n="74" facs="tcp:15204:44"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. How the iudiciall law bindes the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</note>From the morall to come to the Iudiciall law; which was of vſe to preſcribe the Moſaicall forme of ciuill gouernment, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the order offices of Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates and Magiſtracie, iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, puniſhments, contracts, dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of gouernment, to the end that publike iuſtice might bee maintained, peace continued, and the contempt of Gods law reuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged.</p>
            <p>This Law ſo farre bindeth the conſcience now, as it is euer duely grounded vpon the morall, and where the ſame reaſon holdeth thus, as it did in them and other nations by the light of nature pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed in the ſame manner.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">3. How the ceremoniall law bindes conſcience.</note>Thirdly, the <hi>ceremoniall Law (which treateth of rites and ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies enioyned in the Old Testament, to be obſerued about the outward wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God)</hi> is to bee reduced to
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:15204:44"/> three diſtinct times, according to which times, three rules may bee giuen to ſhew how farre forth <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience</hi> is ſubiect to that.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Rule. </seg>1</label> The firſt rule is this. <hi>Before the death of Chriſt, the ceremoniall law did binde the conſciences of the Iewes, and the Iewes onely, not of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles.</hi> For betwixt Iewes and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, there was a wall of ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Rule. </seg>2</label> The ſecond this. <hi>From the death of Chriſt, to the ouerthrow of the Iewiſh gouernment, the ceremoniall law loſt the force of binding, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came an indifferent thing, either to be vſed or not to be vſed.</hi> Hence it was that <hi>Paul circumciſed Timothy,</hi> but would not circumciſe <hi>Titus.</hi> And the<note n="z" place="margin">Act. 15.</note> 
               <hi>councell</hi> at Ieruſalem, decreed that the Church ſhould abſtaine for a time from things ſtrangled, and from blood; the cauſe of which decree was the <hi>weakeneſſe</hi> of ſome
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:15204:45"/> who of Iewes were made Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans. As yet they did not fully vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the libertie of the new <hi>Teſtament,</hi> therfore for their weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ſake, it was granted that they might vſe ſome Iewiſh ceremonies for a time.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Rule. </seg>3</label> But thirdly, <hi>after the euerſion of the Iewiſh gouernment, and the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulgation of the Goſpell, more largely and cleerely the ceremoniall law alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether ceaſed.</hi> For from that time, the <hi>libertie of Chriſtians</hi> and free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome from Iewiſh ceremonies, was ſo conſpicuous that none of the godly could alleadge their ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance heerein. Wherefore very well ſay the <hi>Schooles,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Leges cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniales iam ſunt mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuae, &amp; mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiferae.</note> 
               <hi>Ceremoniall lawes are now dead and deadly.</hi> Thus we ſee the nature of the <hi>lawes,</hi> au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority ouer the conſcience.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. How the Goſpell bindes.</note>Now we will ſee how the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell bindes the <hi>conſcience.</hi> For the better vnderſtanding of which, we
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:15204:45"/> muſt know that the Goſpell doth not binde the conſciences of thoſe that are not called, but onely of them that are called. That it doth not binde the vncalled, it is plaine. Becauſe as they <hi>which ſinne without the Law, ſhall periſh without the Law</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 2.12.</note>; ſo they which ſinne with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Goſpell, ſhall periſh with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Goſpell, but they which periſh without the Goſpell, are not bound by the Goſpell; therefore the vncalled are not bound by the Goſpell. Secondly, that it bindes theſe that are called, I meane ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from Pagans and Infidels, it is manifeſt alſo by this reaſon. <hi>All thoſe that are</hi> called, ſhall be iudged at the laſt day by the Goſpell, as is to be ſeene, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.16. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.15.18. But it is neceſſary that <hi>that ſame thing,</hi> by which men ſhall be iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged after this life, ſhould binde their conſciences in this life: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:15204:46"/> the Goſpell bindes the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of the called. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
               </label> But what doth it binde them vnto? <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> To be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue the promiſes of iuſtification, ſaluation, ſpeciall prouidence, and loue.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
               </label> Yea but <hi>hypocrites are called into the Church,</hi> and if they be bound to beleeue their ſaluation, they are bound to beleeue that which is falſe, for the promiſes of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, concerning the fauour of God, pardon of ſinne, &amp;c. belong not to them. I anſwer, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> That they which are called into the Church, are not abſolutely bound to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue their owne ſaluation, but on this condition, (according to the tenour of the couenant) that <hi>they deſire</hi> truly to be in the number of Chriſts true Diſciples. But to bee the true ſchollers and Diſciples of Chriſt, to learne of him, to follow him, hypocrites doe not ſeriouſly
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:15204:46"/> deſire: therefore their conſciences are not abſolutely bound to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue their owne ſaluation.</p>
            <p>Thus thou vnderſtandeſt how <hi>conſcience</hi> is to be ſubiect to things that doe <hi>immediately binde it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now as touching the things that doe binde it <hi>mediately,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Things mediate to to oblige conſcience.</note> (that is, not of themſelues, but by vertue of that obligatory power, that they haue from the word of God) they are foure: firſt, <hi>the lawes of man:</hi> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, <hi>oathes:</hi> thirdly, <hi>vowes:</hi> fourthly, <hi>promiſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Concerning the firſt, how farre forth conſcience is to ſubmit to humane lawes, thou ſhalt know if thou markeſt theſe foure rules fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing.</p>
            <p>Concerning the firſt, how hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane <hi>lawes doe</hi> binde wee ſhall know,<note place="margin">Rules to vnderſtand the ſubiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience to Mans laws.</note> if wee ponder theſe foure <hi>Rules.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lawes of men, whither they bee
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:15204:47"/> Ciuill or Eccleſiaſticall, doe binde the conſcience</hi> ſo farre forth as they are agreeable to Gods Law. 2. As they <hi>conſerue order, or keepe from confuſion and doe not take away Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian libertie.</hi> 3. For if they haue theſe conditions, they are obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie, and binding by vertue of the fift commandement. <hi>Honour, thy father,</hi> and particular precept giuen by Saint <hi>Paul; Let euery ſoule be ſubiect to the higher power</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Rom. 13.1.</note>. But if it ſo fall out, that theſe <hi>lawes</hi> conſtituted by men, be not about things indifferent, but <hi>good</hi> in themſelues, that is to ſay comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of God, then they are not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly <hi>humane</hi> but <hi>diuine:</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doe altogether binde the <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</hi> Laſtly, if thoſe lawes doe preſcribe things that are euill, they are ſo farre from hauing any pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ouer the conſcience, that the <hi>conſcience</hi> is moſt ſtrictly bound
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:15204:47"/> not to obey them<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Act 4.19.</hi> Conſcientijs velle domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nari eſt ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem coeli in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uadere.</note>. Wherefore we plainly affirme againſt the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the Papiſts, that <hi>neither Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill nor Eccleſiaſticall iuriſdiction, hath any</hi> CONSTRAINING or <hi>compulſiue power</hi> immediately and directly <hi>ouer the conſcience:</hi> ſo that it was well ſaid of <hi>Maximilian</hi> the Emperour, <hi>to ſeeke to domineere o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the conſcience, is impudently to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uade the tower of heauen;</hi> And of<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Cited by</hi> Alſtedius in Theol. Caſ. c. <hi>2</hi> p. <hi>10.</hi> Tria ſunt homini im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſsibilia, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Pſychoty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranno pluſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raonicam, &amp; Phalaricam.</p>
               </note> 
               <hi>Stephanus King of Polonia, Three things are impoſsible to man, to make ſomething of nothing, to know things to come, and to rule or Lord it ouer the conſcience.</hi> That ſame <hi>Pſycho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyranny,</hi> therefore of the Papiſt which is moſt <hi>cruell,</hi> moſt <hi>Pharoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call,</hi> doe we deteſt and abhorre.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Rule. </seg>2,</label> Secondly, the POLITIKE <hi>lawes of man haue ſo farre an obligatory power in the conſcience, that the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating of them, eſpecially if it be ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned either with the offence of their
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:15204:48"/> brethren or contempt of authoritie, it is iuſtly to be accounted for a ſinne</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God, though not immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Rule. </seg>3</label> Thirdly, the ECCLESIASTI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CALL <hi>lawes of men, are either of things neceſſarie without which an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and decorum cannot be kept in the Church, or elſe of things indifferent.</hi> Thoſe that are of things neceſſary, doe binde by the force of that <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine law</hi> written by <hi>Paul, Let all things be done decently and in good order</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Cor.</note>. They that are of things meerely indifferent doe not binde ſo ſtrictly, except the neglect of the ſame, occaſioneth offence to the weake, or be with contempt of Eccleſiaſticall authoritie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This for information</hi> about the mediate binding of <hi>conſcience,</hi> by humane <hi>lawes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, An oath bindes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,<note place="margin">How an oath binde conſcience.</note> if it hath theſe foure condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:15204:48"/> Firſt, <hi>if</hi> (for the matter of it) <hi>it be of things certaine and poſsible.</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, <hi>if</hi> (for manner) <hi>it be made or taken without guile, ſincerely and honeſtly.</hi> Thirdly, <hi>if</hi> (for the end) <hi>it be to Gods glory, or the publike good.</hi> Fourthly, <hi>if</hi> (for the author) <hi>it bee taken by thoſe who haue power ſo to binde themſelues.</hi> Therefore <hi>Herods</hi> oath did not binde his conſcience, becauſe it did not tend to Gods glory, and was of a thing beyond his commiſſion, with warrant to performe. But if an oath hath (I ſay) thoſe conditions, it bindeth by the vertue of that commandement which <hi>Moſes</hi> layes downe. <hi>Numb.</hi> 30.2. <hi>If a man ſweare an oath, to binde his ſoule with a bond, he ſhall not breake his word, he ſhall doe according to all that proceedeth out of his mouth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now in the third place, for the ſubiection <hi>of conſcience to vowes.</hi>
               <note place="margin">3. How vowes binde con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</note> We muſt vnderſtand that <hi>vowes</hi>
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:15204:49"/> are of three ſorts, <hi>morall, ceremoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all,</hi> and <hi>free.</hi> A <hi>morall vow,</hi> is that promiſe of morall obedience to the law of God made in Baptiſme, <hi>renued in the Lords Supper.</hi> And this bindes all Chriſtians at all times. A <hi>ceremoniall vow,</hi> is a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of ceremoniall obedience in the Old Teſtament, ſuch as was the vow of the Nazarites<note n="e" place="margin">Leu. 27.</note>. And this did onely binde thoſe who made it. A <hi>free vow,</hi> is a promiſe of performing ſome outward thing, vndertaken for the cauſe of exerciſing pietie, <hi>as vowes of faſting</hi> or the like, for furtherance in the exerciſe of prayer, of repentance, &amp;c. And this is of a binding pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, if there be in it; firſt, a congrui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie with the word of God; ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, no repugnancie with our cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling; thirdly, if it be no ſpoyler of Chriſtian libertie; and finally, be not made out of an opinion of any
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:15204:49"/> meriting thereby. If (I ſay) it be thus qualified and limited, it binds conſcience by the power of that diuine precept; which is in <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 5.4, 5. <hi>When thou voweſt a vow to God, deferre not to pay it; Better it is thou ſhouldeſt not vow, then that thou ſhouldest vow and not pay.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, that thou maieſt know how <hi>promiſes doe binde the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence;</hi>
               <note place="margin">4. How promiſes binde con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</note> thou muſt obſerue this rule. <hi>That a ſimple promiſe</hi> (I meane di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed from a promiſe, mixt and bound with an oath, <hi>it doth ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige and binde the conſcience at the will of him, to whom it is made,</hi> ſo that if he to whom thou makeſt it, will releaſe thee from the performance of it, thou art free<note n="*" place="margin">See pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes are debts.</note>: if he require it, thou art bound in conſcience to make it good; if ſo be it hath theſe requiſites.</p>
            <p>If it be firſt not <hi>againſt Gods word:</hi> ſecondly, <hi>not againſt honeſty:</hi> thirdly,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:15204:50"/> 
               <hi>if thou beest ſuch an one as haſt power to binde thy ſelfe by ſuch a promiſe:</hi> fourthly, <hi>if he whom thou haſt made it vnto, did not circumuent, and get thee in by guile and deceit to make it:</hi> fiftly, <hi>if the performance of it remaine poſsible and lawfull.</hi> If it hath theſe conditions; it bindes by vertue of the ninth commandement. Thus of theſe things conſiderable about the binding and ſubiection of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, muſt thou get knowledge and information of, if thou wouldeſt not ſtreighten conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and ſo wouldeſt preſerue the goodneſſe of it.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. Helpe againſt ſtraighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</note>Secondly, thou muſt take heede of yeelding to doubtings; of yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding I ſay, For tempted to doubt thou ſhalt be, be thy conſcience neuer ſo good, but yeeld not to the ſame; hold Satan worke at the ſtaues end, and when he ſhall ſhoote his darts in this kinde againſt thee,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:15204:50"/> telling thee, <hi>God is thy enemie, thou art not his childe, heauen ſhall not bee opened vnto thee, hell fire is prepared for thee:</hi> (notwithſtanding, <hi>all thy profeſsing and paines taking</hi>) beare them off with the ſhield of faith. If thou let goe the ſoundneſſe of thy confidence, thou wilt ſhrewdly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſh the goodneſſe of thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. The keeping of faith and a good conſcience are ioyned to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, they that make hauocke of the one, will eaſily make ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wracke of the other; take heede therefore of daſhing thy faith vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the rocke of doubtings by yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vnto them.<note place="margin">3. Subor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate help.</note> And to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, take heede alſo of ruſhing vpon the rocke of deſpaire; when the Lord layes his hand in wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome vpon thee, and thou art tempted to deſpaire of euer obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning any helpe from him. When (for reaſons beſt knowne to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe)
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:15204:51"/> he ſhall withdraw the light of his countenance, which with ioy thou wert once wont to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, and thou ſhalt then be temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to thinke, he will neuer viſite thee with his fauour againe: yeeld not to theſe temptations, be not out of hope; but nouriſh, cheriſh, and maintaine thy hope ſtill how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer. For there can be no better way to keepe thy conſcience good and ſound, then to maintaine thy faith againſt doubtings, and thy hope againſt temptations tending to deſpaire. Thus at length I haue found an end of this point, the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe whereof I commit to God, the vſe whereof I commend to thee; haſtening now to the ſecond part of the text. Which is</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The ſecond part of the Text.</note>The accuſation it ſelfe, which theſe accuſers brought in againſt themſelues, in theſe words.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:15204:51"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:15204:52"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:15204:52"/>
            <head>The Table of the ſecond part.</head>
            <list>
               <item>2. <hi>The Accuſation which the Accuſers bring in, in which note</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. <hi>The di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion and interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, wher</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>1. <hi>The forme, H. V.</hi> We are verily guiltie, <hi>with the meaning of it.</hi> p. 89.</item>
                           <item>2. <hi>The mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which is a caſe of wrong, in which wrong wee haue</hi> 3. <hi>things,</hi>
                              <list>
                                 <item>1. <hi>The obiect or partie wronged, H. V.</hi> concerning our brother, <hi>with the ſenſe.</hi> p. 89.</item>
                                 <item>2. <hi>The Subiect or wrong it ſelfe aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uated by two phraſes.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>3. <hi>The Effect, H. V.</hi> Therefore is this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe come vpon vs: <hi>with the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</hi> p. 91.
<list>
                                       <item>1. We ſaw the anguiſh of his ſoule, <hi>with the ſenſe.</hi> p. 90.</item>
                                       <item>2. When hee beſought vs, we would not heare, <hi>with the ſenſe.</hi> p. 90.</item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. <hi>The do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines which are,</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>1. <hi>Propounded together, appearing to be fiue in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber.</hi> pag. 92.</item>
                           <item>2. <hi>Handled a part.</hi>
                              <list>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>The firſt, or third in the order of the text.</hi> (That in confeſſion of ſinne, wee muſt be ingenious,) <hi>pag.</hi> 93.</item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>The ſecond or fourth,</hi> (That conſcience is a faithfull recorder,) <hi>pag.</hi> 101.</item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>The third or fift in order,</hi> (That by how much the neerer bonds we are tied to one another, by ſo much the ſorer torment ſhall we meete with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in our conſciences,) <hi>pag.</hi> 123.</item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>The fourth or ſixt in order,)</hi> That they ſhall be requited, like for like which offer wrong,) <hi>pag.</hi> 130.</item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>The fift or last in the Text,</hi> (That not to pittie others in their diſtreſſe, is to ſhut vp the bowels of others a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs in our diſtreſſe. <hi>pag.</hi> 142.</item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>To the end.</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:15204:53"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="part">
            <pb n="89" facs="tcp:15204:53"/>
            <head>We are verily guilty concerning our brother, in that we ſaw the anguiſh of his ſoule when he beſought vs, and wee would not heare; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is this diſtreſſe come vpon vs.</head>
            <p>WHEREIN we haue to note,<note place="margin">The ſecond part ſub-di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided, and the words interpreted promiſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly.</note> both the forme and the matter of the accuſation.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The forme in theſe words <hi>[We are verily guilty]</hi> that is, euen <hi>we Iudah,</hi> Since <hi>Leui,</hi> and the reſt of vs brethren, are moſt certainly, truly without all flattery guiltie. 2. The matter in the reſidue of the verſe, which is a caſe of iniury or wrong; where we are to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: firſt, the <hi>obiect:</hi> ſecondly, the <hi>ſubiect:</hi> thirdly, the <hi>effect</hi> of the wrong. 1. The <hi>obiect</hi> was <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> he was the man to whom they had done the wrong, which they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe themſelues off heere, and him they call brother <hi>[concerning our
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:15204:54"/> brother]</hi> for ſo he was indeede, by fathers ſide, though not by mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſide. 2. The <hi>ſubiect</hi> of the wrong or the wrong it ſelf, (which they had offered that their bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) they doe aggrauate againſt themſelues by two phraſes; firſt, <hi>[wee ſaw the anguiſh of his ſoule,]</hi> that is to ſay: wee wretches after we had firſt caſt him into the pit, and then ſold him to the Midia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites, we could looke vpon his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe and perplexitie, with drie eyes without teares, and ſo our eyes were vnmercifull vnto him: ſecondly, <hi>[when he beſought vs, wee would not heare]</hi> yea, whereas it had behooued vs vpon the very ſight of his anguiſh, to haue decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed from our cruelty; he did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech vs, entreat vs to ſpare him, &amp; let him alone, yet we were ſo hard-hearted, that we would not conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend vnto his entreaty, and ſo
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:15204:54"/> our hearts and eares were vnmer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull vnto him. Thirdly, the <hi>effect</hi> of the wrong following, in theſe words: <hi>[therefore is this diſtreſſe come vpon vs]</hi> yea, therefore we are now ſerued like for like, this <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe of vs being charged for ſpies, clapped vp in priſon, cannot be heard to pleade and apologize for our ſelues, one of vs muſt now bee laide vp in chaines,</hi> and God knowes how cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elly he ſhall be vſed ere we come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine: <hi>this diſtreſſe is come vpon vs.</hi> If we ioyne theſe branches toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in a paraphraſe, we may ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine theſe brethren to bring in this accuſation againſt themſelues in theſe termes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Come brethren come,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſe.</note> 
               <hi>why ſtand we pauſing with our ſelues, what this hard-ſhip meaneth, whence it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth? Wee euen wee are moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly without any diſſembling or flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, guiltie of offering great wrong to
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:15204:55"/> our owne brother, the ſonne of our a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged father, wee caſt him into the pit, we ſold him into the hands of Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Merchants, wee looked vpon him and laughed at him, when wee ſaw the dreamer in perplexitie, he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated vs by the bond of fraternitie with teares to ſpare him, not to deale ſo hardly with him, and we ſtopt our eares againſt his cry, we regarded not his requeſt, would ſhow no kindneſſe to him, haue no compaſsion on him, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are we brought into this miſery. Now loe we, we are paide home to the full, we are recompenced like for like; This gouernour of the land lookes vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the anguiſh of our ſoule, we entreate him, he will not vouchſafe to heare vs, nor beleeue vs.</hi> This is the ſumme, heere is the ſence.</p>
            <p>The concluſions follow, and are fiue.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Confeſsion</hi> of ſinne muſt bee ingenuous.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:15204:55"/>2. <hi>Conſcience</hi> keepes a true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſter.</p>
            <p n="3">3. By how much neerer bonds we are tyed to one another, by ſo much ſorer torment are we like to feele in our conſciences for the wrongs we doe them.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>God requites like for like to the wrong doer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. They that are pittileſſe to their brethren in the time of their diſtreſſe, ſhall finde others pittileſſe to themſelues in their diſtreſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>3</label> To begin with the firſt. <hi>In the confeſsing of faults, we muſt be inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuous,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Confeſſion of ſinnes muſt be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuous.</note> that is, we muſt deale truly without hypocriſie, throughly without ſecrecy or hiding any of our euils; ſo dealt theſe brethren of <hi>Ioſeph</hi> heere, charging them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to be <hi>verily guiltie,</hi> without fayning or doubting, or laying the fault vpon one another; and eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry particular in the wrong, doe
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:15204:56"/> they without hiding confeſſe and acknowledge, as firſt how they had looked vpon and laughed at his diſtreſſe: ſecondly, how they had ſtopped their eares againſt his cry. This ingenuity wee finde in <hi>Dauid,</hi> who when he was found guilty by <hi>Nathans</hi> ſermon; he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed his whole ſinne. <hi>I haue ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned against the Lord.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Sam. 12.13.</note> Marke, hee doth not ſay, I haue committed adultery alone, or I am guiltie of murther onely, but he ſaith, <hi>I haue ſinned.</hi> I am truly guiltie of all that thou haſt charged mee withall. Neither ſaith he, I haue ſinned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Bathſheba,</hi> againſt <hi>Vriah onely, but againſt the Lord,</hi> as well as they; Iuſt ſo deales he in confeſſion, after hee had ſinned in numbring the people; where he confeſſeth that he had not ſimply ſinned, but <hi>ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned greatly in that which hee had done</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">2. Sam. 24.10.</note>. This is euident in <hi>Nehemiahs</hi>
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:15204:56"/> prayer<note n="c" place="margin">Nehem. 1.6, 7.</note>, where making confeſſion, he doth not onely co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe his own ſinnes, but the ſinnes of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, wherein hee acknowledged himſelfe to haue a ſhare, neither doth he onely <hi>confeſſe</hi> their ſinnes of commiſſion, in ſaying, <hi>we haue dealt very corruptly againſt thee,</hi> but alſo of omiſſion, ſaying, <hi>we haue not kept the commandements, nor the ſtatutes, nor the iudgements which thou commandeſt thy ſeruant Moſes.</hi> The very like we haue in <hi>Daniels</hi> prayer, <hi>and confeſsion. We haue ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and haue committed iniquitie, and haue done wickedly, and haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belled, &amp;c. Neither haue we hearke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to thy ſeruants, the Prophets, which ſpake in thy name,</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Dan. 9.5, 6.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the rather muſt wee deale thus ingenuouſly in the confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſinne, becauſe we muſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake all ſinne, and ſorrow for all ſinne in good earneſt, now if all
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:15204:57"/> ſinne muſt bee ſorrowed for, and that without all hypocriſie, if all ſinne muſt be abandoned, and in good earneſt abandoned, then it muſt as generally as ſeriouſly bee confeſſed and acknowledged.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> Doe not they then much tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe this rule,<note place="margin">Reproofe.</note> who are ſo farre from confeſſing all their ſinnes, that they will confeſſe none of them, like the proud Phariſee iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying themſelues, when as Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canes and harlots, who amongſt the Iewes were accounted com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly the worſt of the people, are like to enter into the kingdome of heauen as ſoone as they? Doe not they alſo offend this rule, who wil confeſſe ſome of their ſinnes, but not all of them? if they be noted for ſwearing, drunkenneſſe, or ſome other profane acts they haue committed, happily they will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe them vnto God, vnto men, but
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:15204:57"/> for their more ſecret euils, which man cannot directly charge them withall, theſe they confeſſe not, theſe they acknowledge not, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to God who is able to pardon them, nor to men who are fit to pray for them, to giue direction vnto them, how to be freed from the ſame.</p>
            <p>Againſt both theſe ſorts, I may vrge not onely the preſent exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in my text for their reproofe; but alſo the words of an holy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Church.<note place="margin">Aug. in lib. <hi>50.</hi> hom. <hi>12.</hi> circa finem. Tu feciſti, tu reus es, ſi autem dicas non ego fec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, vbicunque verba excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa re volue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum tuum manet in te, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Thou haſt ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, thou art guiltie. If therefore thou ſhalt ſay, I HAVE NOT SINNED, excuſe thoſe words how thou wilt, thy ſinne remaineth in thee, of ſinne thou art guiltie, and not onely of that ſinne, which thou diddeſt lately commit</hi> (&amp; wilt not confeſſe) <hi>but alſo of pride, becauſe thou wilt not confeſſe.</hi> And doth it indeede ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare by that father that not to
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:15204:58"/> confeſſe ſinne, is an addition to ſinne, an argument of pride and want of humilitie? then thinke thou what little wrong I doe thee, to reprooue thee, who either ſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt to confeſſe thy ſinnes at all, or refuſeſt ſo ingenuouſly to open them all to the Lord, as thou oughteſt, which tell mee, thou wouldeſt obtaine pardon for all, wouldeſt thou not? thou wouldeſt not be condemned for any, woul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt thou? I tell thee, except thou doeſt<note n="*" place="margin">A ſpeech often vſed by S <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>agnoſcere,</hi> God will not <hi>ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſcere,</hi> without <hi>confeſsion</hi> no <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion. For the acknowledging of our faults, is the aboliſhing of our faults</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Confeſsio enim pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum, abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litio delicto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſt. in Gen. Hom. <hi>19.</hi>
               </note>. Oh folly then that it is for thee whoſoeuer thou beeſt, to make thy ſoule lyable to confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on heereafter, for want of a ſincere and ingenuous confeſſion of thy ſinnes in this life. I would I could perſwade thee to the contrary, oh
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:15204:58"/> that the Lord would be pleaſed to make me an inſtrument of tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching thee better wiſedome.<note place="margin">Exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> 
               <hi>Get thee</hi> I pray thee, get thee into ſome ſecret place, ſift the corners of thy ſoule, deale ingenuouſly and plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with the Lord; thinke it not enough to confeſſe ſome of thy ſinnes, but all of them, not onely the leſſe but alſo the greater, and the leſſe as well as the greater, bring before him all the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, the manner how, the time when, the occaſions where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the meanes by which the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies againſt which thou haſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the ſame.<note place="margin">A caution.</note> I perſwade thee not to auriculer confeſſion as the Church of Rome enioynes her penitents; but to that which <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid,</hi> and <hi>Peter,</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> haue vſed; to confeſſe to God, and in caſe of neceſſitie to ſome faithfull Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, to ſome Chriſtian brother:
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:15204:59"/> when as otherwiſe thy conſcience cannot bee ſetled and ſatisfied.<note place="margin">Plurimum enim ad pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catae emen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danda valet confeſsio. Chryſoſt. in Gen Hom. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> Alas, what will it auaile thee to hide any of thy ſinnes, when as the Lord knowes all thy ſinnes. And how canſt thou truly amend any one, when as thou wilt not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge euery one. How high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly doth one of the<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <p>Aug. ad fra. in Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo. Hom. <hi>30. 2.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Diſsipatrix vitiorum, reſtaura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trix virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, &amp;c.</p>
               </note> Ancients ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toll this duty, calling it, <hi>the diſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of vices, the reſtorer of vertues, the oppugner of Deuils. Oh holy and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable confeſsion, thou ſtoppeſt vp the mouth of hell, thou openeſt the gates of heauen. Nothing ſhall remaine in iudgement againſt them, who are by this purged from their ſinnes.</hi> I might vſe many arguments to perſwade to this, but time would faile mee, neither doth the text in hand re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire it of mee; The treatiſes of repentance haue done it for mee, onely that which I wiſh thee vnto, is ingenuitie in confeſſing to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:15204:59"/> hypocriſie and doe it ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely, to auoyde partiality, and doe it throughly, as well concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſinnes <hi>of omiſsion as commiſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> of failing in the manner of good duties, as neglecting the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; plaine dealing is alwaies the beſt, and is that which will bring moſt reſt vnto thy ſoule. Hoping that this ſhal ſuffice to mooue thee, I leaue this doctrine and proceede to the next which is this.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>4</label> 
               <hi>That the conſcience keepes a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full regiſter.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Conſcience is a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</note> 
               <hi>See</hi> heere what a true record of that wrong offered to <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph,</hi> the conſciences of theſe bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren tooke, and kept.</p>
            <p>It had ſet downe euery circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in the ſame, how they had beene pittileſſe vnto him, ſtopt vp their eares againſt him, yea (as it is very probable) how they had gul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led their aged father concerning him, making him beleeue that
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:15204:60"/> ſome euill beaſt had deuoured him; Conſcience had not loſt one whit of the cruelty, the villany they had committed againſt him, but had ſet downe euery iot and title of the ſame. Such an infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble regiſter of <hi>Iobs</hi> deedes, did the conſcience of <hi>Iob</hi> take, the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars whereof, it preſents vnto him in the time of his extreamitie, as is euident in ſundry places of his booke. In one place remembring his perſeuerance in grace, his loue to the word. <hi>My feete hath held his ſteppes, his waies haue I kept, and not declined. Neither haue I gone backe from the commandement of his lippes: I haue eſteemed the words of his mouth more then mine appointed foode</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Iob 23.11, 12.</note>. In another place preſenting his <hi>iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and righteouſneſſe,</hi> his charitie and mercifulneſſe to the poore<note n="h" place="margin">Chap. 29.12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 17.</note>. <hi>I deliuered the poore that cryed, and the fatherleſſe and him that had none to
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:15204:60"/> helpe him; The bleſsing of him that was ready to periſh came vpon mee, I cauſed the widdowes heart to ſing for ioy. I put on righteouſneſſe and it cloathed mee, my iudgement was as a robe and a diadem. I was eyes to the blinde, and feete to the lame. I was a father to the poore, &amp;c.</hi> In another place remembring his obedience: <hi>I made a couenant with mine eyes, that I would not looke vpon a maide to luſt after her. I haue not walked with vanitie, neither hath my foote haſted to deceit,</hi> that whole 31. chapter being nothing elſe but a regiſter of his obedience, which his conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence had ſet downe before for his comfort againſt that time of need; What ſhall I ſpeake of <hi>Dauid, Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah</hi> and the reſt, whoſe goodneſſe was recorded in their owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, whatſoeuer the wicked did goe about to accuſe, and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe them withall. What a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:15204:61"/> regiſter of <hi>Pharaohs</hi> iniuries a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Iſraelites<note n="i" place="margin">Exod. 10.16.</note>, of the Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites againſt <hi>Samuel</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">1. Sam. 12.14.</note>, of <hi>Saules</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Dauid</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Chap. 24.17.</note>, of <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phira</hi> againſt the <hi>Primitiue Church</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Act. 5.2.</note>, all their conſciences had taken, the word of God doth record, and ſome of their owne mouthes did report. Hence it is that <hi>conſcience</hi> is compared to a booke; For looke as in a booke, men ſet downe things which they would haue faithfully remembred, ſo the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience takes notice of thoſe things which man muſt and ſhall remember. Hence is that vſuall prouerbe amongſt vs. <hi>The conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is a thouſand witneſſes. Why ſo?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>1</label> Firſt, God is the Lord of the conſcience, now the Lord is the God of truth, cannot deceiue, and therefore whatſoeuer he ſets down in the conſcience muſt needs bee true, what euer he that commands
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:15204:61"/> the conſcience, will haue the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience keepe, muſt bee faithfull, and hence it is, that it takes and keepes ſo infallible a bill and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>2</label> Secondly, the conſcience goes not ſlightly and careleſly to work, in taking an account of things, but ſolidely and ſubſtantially, it maketh ſure worke: For in the minde (which ſence make the ſeate of conſcience) there are three faculties, which are as it were the parts of conſcience. 1. There is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence either
<list>
                  <item>contemplatiue,</item>
                  <item>or practicall.</item>
               </list> 2. There is election. 3. There is iudgement or the facultie of iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catory. Now each of theſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formeth a ſeuerall office. Firſt, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence contemplatiue, hath an office <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> out, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> principles
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:15204:62"/> and grounds for information; In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence practicall, to make or draw out practicall minors, for practicall ſyllogiſmes, from thoſe principles which contemplation findes out, or, if you will more plainly, it is of office to ſhew tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly what <hi>we</hi> haue done, or what <hi>we</hi> haue not done for our owne parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular. Secondly, Election is of vſe to ioyne maiors to thoſe minors, that is to ſhew vs that that is good or not good, euill or not euill which wee haue done. Thirdly, iudgement or the iudiciall facultie (as I ſaid) is exerciſed in pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing the reward, or the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment due for what we haue done. Now then if conſcience be buſied about true grounds for informati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, if ſecondly vpon theſe grounds it ſhewes vs directly what particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar things <hi>We</hi> haue done, nor not done, if thirdly, it ſhowes the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:15204:62"/> of the things that wee haue done, and that they be either ſuch as ought to be done, or ought not to be done; if finally it pronounces truly the reward due, or the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment due, muſt it not needes take a faithfull account, and be a faithfull recorder of our deedes? I can ſee nothing to the contrary. If <hi>Iob</hi> or <hi>Dauid,</hi> &amp;c. haue the gift of generall vnderſtanding in the word, of particular or practicall vnderſtanding of themſelues and their owne actions, if they can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude from that word that ſuch things ought to be auoided or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, and that they in iuſtice and equitie are ſo and ſo to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded, is it much to be maruei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, that their conſciences could ſo faithfully report vnto them their owne innocency and integritie; Truly no more to be wondered at, then if a man ſhould ſet downe
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:15204:63"/> ſome true exploite done by ſome other in a note booke, when hee hath a faithfull informer, to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint him, with what the exploite was, who the perſon was that did it, when the time of the doing of it was; and what reward he had for his labour after he had done it.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> To ſundry endes and vſes ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth the meditation of this point.</p>
            <p>The firſt is the glory of God. If the heauens declare the glory of God as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſheweth,<note place="margin">Pſal. 19.1.</note> &amp; the firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhew forth his handy worke, vndoubtedly the conſcience of man can do no leſſe. The one is the booke of nature as well as the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, It is true, there is ſome dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference betwixt them, for the one is internall written on the inſide, the other externall written on the outſide; yet heerein they agree, that both of them containe in them Lectures of the Makers
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:15204:63"/> praiſes. Is his wiſedome magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the booke of the creatures? And is it not as well in the booke of the conſcience? Is his goodnes manifeſt in the one, and not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuous in the other? Doth the one ſhew forth the praiſe of his power, and not the other declare the glory of his greatneſſe? Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull is the Lord in all workes<note n="m" place="margin">Miran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum ſane o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pificium Dei in homini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus eſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientia. Heming Synt. p. <hi>156.</hi>
               </note>? wonderfull alſo in this one of his workes: His wiſedome wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, his mercy wonderfull, his power wonderfull, I may adde alſo his iuſtice wonderfull. His wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome (I ſay) for all the Art of man cannot inuent ſo exquiſite a thing, cannot pen ſo faithfull a record as <hi>conſcience</hi> is. Prognoſticators that fetch their wiſedome from the Perſians, who were once accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the great Sophiſts of the world<note n="*" place="margin">Diogen. Laert Vit. Phyloſoph. l. <hi>1.</hi> p. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note>; Hiſtorians that fetch their knowledge, either by the eye from
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:15204:64"/> that which they behold, or by the eare from that which they heare may compoſe Kalenders, pen Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumes, yet may faile in many things they ſet down, and deceiue themſelues and their readers? but in this volume of mans conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, whatſoeuer the Lord of the conſcience ſets downe, be it good or euill, it is moſt infallibly and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly true. 2. His<note n="n" place="margin">Quod &amp; ipſum diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae miſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordiae est, quae homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem generi conceſsit, vt vnicuique noſtrum niſi tum eſſet in deprauabile iudicium conſcientiae &amp;c. Chryſoſt. in Gen. Hom. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> mercy is wonderfull, in that he giues a man ſo faithfull a recorder, to ſet downe all the good acts that for Gods glory he vndertaketh and perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth; and to ſuggeſt vnto his thoughts all his failings, that hee may quickly turne vnto the Lord from them and recouer. 3. His power is wonderfull in that he can rule the <hi>conſcience in deſpite of Satan, to excuſe a man with the regiſter of his integritie,</hi> let Satan tempt him to deſpaire, to accuſe a man with
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:15204:64"/> the recordes of his iniquities, let the deuill labour what hee can to make him ſecure. Laſtly, his iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice is wonderfull, in that he hath made this conſcience as a continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all witneſſe in the wicked mans heart, to challenge him without failing for euery thing wherein he is guiltie; wherefore (good Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) whenſoeuer thou thinkeſt vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the faithfulneſſe of conſcience in keeping of recordes, be not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getfull to giue the Lord the due glory of theſe his attributes, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing and ſhewing forth them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in this wonderfull and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable worke of the conſcience.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> Secondly, doth conſcience keep a faithfull regiſter? then be we ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhed in the feare of God, to take heede of committing ſinne in ſecret. For <hi>conſcience</hi> will record it, and ſet it downe, that is moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine. The twy-light will little
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:15204:65"/> auaile the adulterer to take his fill of luſt in; the night will little profit the ſwaggerer to be drunke in; the darke ſhoppe will little ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage the deceiuer to cheate in; The wiping of the mouth, the cleanſing of the out ſide of the cuppe, the new moones, the ſprea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding abroad of the hands, &amp;c. will little auaile the hypocrite, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure widdowes houſes withall, to couer his iniuſtice, the malice in his heart, the blood in his hands withall. Conſcience hath ſuch piercing eyes, that it can ſee in the darke, it is ſuch an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Scriuener, it can write in the darke. Goe thou about the deeds of darkneſſe after the darkeſt man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner that can be, it takes notice of all, it will pen down euery iot, tit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, and circumſtance in all. I tell thee in the Court of thy Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence the Law is written, that thy
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:15204:65"/> faults may abound, in thy remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, and that it may bring<note n="o" place="margin">Vt &amp; ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tera &amp; la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentia de li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cta in lucem pro ducat. Brent. in Rom. <hi>1343.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>both thy olde and ſecret ſinnes to light;</hi> beware therefore in any caſe, not onely of open and groſſe ſinnes, but alſo of ſecret and cloſe ſinnes. It was well ſaid of a<note n="p" place="margin">Tertull. de Idololat. p. <hi>735.</hi> cur enim &amp; la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teas, cum ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norantia al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terius tuam conſcientiam contamines.</note> 
               <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine. Why keepeſt thou cloſe, when as with the ignorance of another thou defileſt thine owne conſcience.</hi> It was well ſaid by an<note n="q" place="margin">Senec. l. <hi>1.</hi> ep. <hi>43.</hi> ad calcem. Si turpiae quid refert neminem ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, cum tu ſcias.</note> Heathen. <hi>If the thing bee diſhoneſt which thou doeſt, what wil it auaile, though no man know it, if thou thy ſelfe be priuie to it.</hi> Yea what will it <hi>profite thee, though all men ſhould praiſe thee, if thine owne conſcience doth accuſe thee</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Gregor. in Ezek hom. <hi>9.</hi> Quid enim prodeſt ſi om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos laudent, &amp; conſcientia accuſat. Mihi ſufficit conſcientia mea. Aug. ad fr. Her. <hi>5.53.</hi>
               </note>. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (I ſay) auoide that which is ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hominable in Gods ſight: let not the moſt ſecret place encourage thee to any ſinfull practiſe, alwaies remembring this, that thy ſecreteſt
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:15204:66"/> euils are not onely ſet before the ſight of Gods countenance, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo noted downe in the booke of thine owne conſcience, which one day ſhall be opened to thine eternall ſhame, without ſerious and ſpeedie repentance.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>3</label> Thirdly, here is comfort to all Chriſtians againſt thoſe euill ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes that are vniuſtly conceiued againſt them, againſt thoſe contu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melious ſpeeches that are wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully vttered of them. Some charge thee peraduenture with this thing to diſgrace thee, others with that, to take away thy name from thee, as the Iewes charged Chriſt, to be a coniurer,<note n="ſ" place="margin">Math. 12.24.</note> 
               <hi>Iohn</hi> Baptiſt a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniacke,<note n="t" place="margin">Math. 11.18.</note> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> a ſeducer<note n="u" place="margin">Act. 19.26. Chap. 24.5</note> 
               <hi>Steuen</hi> a <hi>Blaſphemer</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Act. 6.23.</note>; But haue thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to thy conſcience. That ſame inward witneſſe and iudge, that (I ſay) hath taken a faithfull record of what thou art and haſt
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:15204:66"/> beene, and if that defends thee, what hurt can it be to thee though all ſhould diſgrace thee<note n="x" place="margin">Quid pote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit obeſſe, fi omnes dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent &amp; sola conſcientia defendat. Gregor. in Ezek. hom. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note>. For looke as the <hi>Sicophants</hi> falſe praiſes cannot heale an euill conſcience, no more can the Slaunderers con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumelious ſpeeches, wound a good conſcience. Doe others ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe thee of drunkenneſſe, and thine owne conſcience teſtifie thy ſobrietie, others charge thee with fellony, and thy owne conſcience witneſſe the contrary? doe others raile on thee for hypocriſie, and thy owne conſcience witneſſe thy ſinceritie? &amp;c. Beleeue thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, which is a faithfull teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie, and cannot deceiue thee againſt all thoſe lying obloquies, wherewith euill mouthes goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to depraue thee. The<note n="y" place="margin">Ouid. Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor. lib. <hi>4.</hi> Conſciamens recti fama mendacia ridet.</note> Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then could ſay, that <hi>A minde conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous of its owne honeſtie, laughes to ſcorne lying infamie.</hi> Be then the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:15204:67"/> that are maliciouſly and falſely raiſed of thee, what they can be, let the innocencie of thy conſcience be a<note n="z" place="margin">Murus a heneus eſto nil conſcire ſibi, &amp;c. Horat. Epiſt. l. <hi>1.</hi> Epiſt. ad Maecenaten. Ambroſ. de offic Bene ſibi conſcius falſis non de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet moueri conuitijs, nec aeſtimare plus ponderis in alieno eſſe conuitio quam in ſuo teſtimonio.</note> brazen wall vnto thee to beare and beate of thoſe diſcomforts which by that meane may be occaſioned in thy ſoule. For (as <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſaies worthily. <hi>Hee that hath a cleere conſcience ought not to be troubled, at falſe ſlaunders, neither must he eſteeme another mans reproachfull tale againſt him, of more weight then his owne priuate teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie within him.</hi> Looke thou poore Chriſtian, more to thy <hi>conſcience then fame, for</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Falli nam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que ſaepe po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terit fama, conſcientia nunquam. Senec. Epiſt. <hi>72.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>fame may oftentimes be deceiued,</hi> but <hi>conſcience neuer</hi> in the things which it recordeth.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>4</label> Laſt of all, doth conſcience keepe a faithfull regiſter. How carefull then ought wee to be, to commit the beſt things we can to its cuſtody. How happy will it be for vs, in diſtreſſe at death, and the
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:15204:67"/> day of iudgement, to haue our conſciences produce to our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfort, and our glory, our holy thoughts and meditations, our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uout prayers and ciaculations, our vertues of louing, fearing, depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding on, ſeruing, honouring the God of heauen, our teares and ſighes for our owne ſinnes, and the ſinnes of the times, our ardent wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes, conſcionable endeauours for Sions wel-fare, our denials of our ſelues, our workes of charitie to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the ſoules, perſons, ſtates and names of others, our goodly counſels, Chriſtian inſtructions, holy examples, giuen to them that are yoaked with vs, that are vnder our gouernment, that dwell by vs, that are acquainted with vs? Oh how ſweete, how comfortable a a thing (I ſay) will it be vnto vs, to finde a bedrole, a catalogue of ſuch things as theſe are, when theſe
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:15204:68"/> ſealed bookes (ſealed to the world-ward) of our conſciences come to be opened and vnclaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped? Oh (beloued) if we would haue conſcience faithfully relate theſe things then, let vs carefully labour to haue our ſhare in theſe vertues, let vs conſcionably pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe theſe things now, that conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence may record them, and keepe them, againſt ſuch aftertimes; For whatſoeuer we commit to it, it is an infallible, and truſty keeper of it. It is (as<note n="b" place="margin">Hugo de Anima. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>9.</hi> Aure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um Reclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torium, Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca foederis, Theſauris Regis.</note> one calles it) <hi>a golden cloſet, the Arke of the couenant, the Kings ſtore-houſe:</hi> intimating thus much, that like as in a cloſet a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man layes vp her beſt Iewels, like as in his treaſurie, a King ſtores vp his richeſt treaſures, againſt the time and neede of vſe, like as in the Arke were reſerued the rod of <hi>Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron,</hi> and pot of <hi>Manna,</hi> for a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moriall to the Iſraelites: So in a
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:15204:68"/> good conſcience the precious gemmes of inward graces, the heauenly treaſures, the budding rod of outward vertues, are reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and kept in ſtore, for the Chriſtian that hath them, to be v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by him, when time ſerueth, when neede requireth, to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred of him to his priuate comfort, and to his glory amongſt others, when there is neede of the memoriall. Not one teare ſhed for thy ſinnes, by way of hearty re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, not one prayer made to Gods Maieſtie out of a deuout and contrite ſpirit, not one dutie performed in a conſcionable obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to Gods will, not a cup of cold water giuen to a diſciple, in the name of a Diſciple, but as God ſees it, ſo conſcience notes it: how frequent, how abundant then in theſe and the like yeares, in theſe and the like duties oughteſt thou
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:15204:69"/> to be, that this faithfull notary of thy conſcience may bee ſtuffed with good things for thy comfort, not with euill for thy terrour. What neede of preſſing hath this dutie, in regard of the deſperate careleſneſſe of moſt people? who regard not how emptie of grace, how full of ſinne their hearts be, how voyde of good fruits, how a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounding with euill fruits, their liues be? They care not what I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tems for murther, for theft, for wantonneſſe, for vſurie, briberie, blaſphemie, hypocriſie, coſenage, pride, malice, neglect of the works of pietie to God, of mercy to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards their neighbour, they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to the booke of their conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, as though it were a booke neuer to be opened; as though the doctrine in hand were an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truth, and conſcience an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfull parchment, either full of
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:15204:69"/> blancks, or lyes? In ſtead of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, they will ſweare, in ſtead of bleſſing, they curſe, in ſtead of fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring God, they dare him, of lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing him, they hate him, of tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting in him, they murmure againſt him, of frequenting his houſe, they frequent the ſtewes, the tauerne, the play-houſe, in ſtead of a righteous carriage towards man, their conuerſation is vnrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, in ſtead of a ſober carriage in regard of themſelues, they are moſt intemperate, vnruly, neither can reaſon, nor religion, bridle their affections. Poore <hi>CON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SCIENCE</hi> hath nothing but <hi>THESE</hi> things to record, for the time preſent, to report, to bring forth in time to come; which is a moſt lamentable thing to conſider. I would theſe deſperate creatures, would goe to<hi rend="sup">c</hi> Nature to ſchoole. <hi>An euill conſcience</hi> (ſaith that) <hi>may
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:15204:70"/> oftentimes be ſafe, yet it is neuer ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure,</hi> that is to ſay, although an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill mans conſcience bee many times without preſent terrour, yet it is neuer ſo careleſſe, but it is a recorder, in taking account of thoughts, words, and deedes, it is neuer idle. There's Natures poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: what is the vſe ſhee makes of it? Marke what followes. <hi>Therefore thou ſhalt commit nothing to conſcience,</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Itaque ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil ei com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeris niſi quod amico comittere poſsis.</note> 
               <hi>but what thou maieſt commit to a friend.</hi> And what that is, euery one almoſt knowes; To friends ſecrets are committed, and if our ſecreteſt deedes bee good, conſcience will be our friend to blaze them forth to our comfort and renowne, and that moſt faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, vndeceiueably, though the world takes no knowledge, makes no acknowledgement of the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>5</label> I paſſe on now to the 3. point in the ſecond part of my text.</p>
            <pb n="123" facs="tcp:15204:70"/>
            <p>
               <hi>That by how much the ſtronger the bondes be,</hi>
               <note place="margin">By offering wrong to breake the bonds of vnion, is an aggraua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the hearts hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour.</note> 
               <hi>whereby men are tyed to one another, by ſo much the ſorer the torment is like to be in the conſcience, for the wrongs they offer to one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> It was the breach of the bond of brother-hood that (no doubt) encreaſed the horror of theſe bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren in this their diſtreſſe, doth not their ſpeech bewray as much? <hi>We are verily guilty concerning OVR BROTHER;</hi> this ſame <hi>BRO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THER,</hi> ſtucke much in their ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke. It was the wronging of his <hi>Father,</hi> his louing <hi>Father,</hi> who had giuen him his patrimonie, affected him deerely, ſhowne kindneſſe to him continually, which made the inward gripes the ſtronger, and the outward cries the louder, of the yong prodigall<note n="e" place="margin">Luke 15.18.21.</note>. It was the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traying of his Maſter, his kinde Maſter (who had called him to an Apoſtleſhip, betruſted him with
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:15204:71"/> the Stewardſhip (whom he was ſo bound vnto, that if neede had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, he ſhould rather haue beene prodigall of his owne blood for his ſake, then haue betrayed his innocent blood,) that encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the horrour, the heart-ſmart of <hi>Iudas</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Math. 27.3.</note>. It was no doubt the ſpoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the life, the defiling of the wife of his <hi>Seruant,</hi> his truſty and faithfull <hi>ſeruant Vriah,</hi> (who lay watching and warring in the open fields for <hi>Dauids</hi> ſake, whom <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> was beholding vnto for his loue and ſeruice,) that did aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the trouble of <hi>Dauids</hi> conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, when the Lord in mercy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waked him<note n="g" place="margin">2. Sam. 12.13. Pſal. 51.</note>. Did you neuer reade nor heare of <hi>Nero,</hi> how that the murther of his mother, (whom nature bound him to) and the ſlaughter of his kindred, (whom the ſame bond tyed him to) did ſo vexe and torment him, that neither
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:15204:71"/> day nor night could hee be quiet, but ſtill he thought his mothers ghoſt did appeare vnto him, and the furies of hell were ready at hand to torment him<note n="h" place="margin">Sueton. in vit. Nero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis. c. <hi>34. 35.</hi>
               </note>? The like is ſtoried of <hi>Alexander,</hi> who ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſlaine a deere friend of his named <hi>Clytus,</hi> who had in loue ſhowne his readineſſe to haue died for <hi>Alexander</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Curt. lib. <hi>8.</hi> p. <hi>119.</hi> ſi moriendum eſt pro te, Clytus eſt primus.</note>, was ſo terrified in his minde, that hee would haue killed himſelfe with that weapon wherewith hee ſlew <hi>Clytus,</hi> if his guard had not preuented him, he lay groueling vpon the earth, fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the whole court with miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble howling and out-cries, asked thoſe that ſtood by him, whither they could ſuffer ſuch a <hi>wretch</hi> as himſelfe was to liue, cloiſtered vp himſelfe in his tent, and would haue pined himſelfe to death, if his ſeruants had not by ſtrong hand compelled him to take
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:15204:72"/> meate, ſtill this being his pitti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſong<note n="k" place="margin">Et ego ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uatorum meorum la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tro reuertar in patriam. Curt. lib. ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat. pag. <hi>120. 121. 122.</hi>
               </note>, <hi>I ſhall returne into my owne countrey a murtherer of my SAVERS,</hi> (my <hi>Sauers,</hi>) this ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grauated his horror, this (queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onleſſe) added to his terrour, that hee ſhould ſo wrong one, that had rather beene his ſauer then his enemie, whoſe loue hee was bound (as the light of nature taught him) to haue rewarded in a better kinde. Thus we ſee the truth of the point, how that the ſtrength of bonds, to tie vs to one another, doth encreaſe the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexitie of the conſcience for thoſe iniuries we doe or ſhall offer to one another.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> Heare this, all you, whom no bonds (no not of nature, of blood it ſelfe) can keepe within the compaſſe of loue, of equitie, whoſe hearts are malignant, whoſe tongues are virulent, whoſe cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:15204:72"/> are violent againſt your owne kinred, the father riſing vp againſt the ſonne, the ſonne againſt the father, the mother againſt the daughter, the daughter againſt the mother, husband againſt wife, wife againſt husband, brother againſt brother, ſiſter againſt ſiſter: a mans enemies being not onely of his owne houſe, but alſo of his owne blood; Heare you I ſay, this word of the Lord, take it in by the eare, and apply it to the heart. Poore wretches, what wrong doe you of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer your owne conſciences? you pile vp horror for them, you trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure vp terror againſt them. The ſtronger the knots be to binde you to vnity, the ſorer ſhall your an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh be for your fruits of enmitie. <hi>Achitophel</hi> ſtood but in a ciuill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to <hi>Dauid,</hi> as a <hi>ſubiect</hi> to his Prince, yet hee was terrified for giuing euill counſell againſt
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:15204:73"/> him<note n="l" place="margin">2. Sam. 17.23.</note>, They Iaylor but in a dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall relation to <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas,</hi> as a Iaylor to his priſoners, yet hee was affrighted for laying bolts vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them<note n="m" place="margin">Act. 16.24.30.</note>. And doe you thinke that you may offer vnnaturall vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, to thoſe; betwixt whom and you there is naturall refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, and your conſciences will neuer accuſe you? as ſure as can be you are deceiued. Let but bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren in the ſame Eccleſiaſticall function, fellow Magiſtrates in the ſame temporall vocation, fellow ſeruants in the ſame family, fellow neighbours in the ſame countrey, offer wrong to one another. I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not warrant <hi>THEM</hi> ſecuritie from ſtings of conſcience. But to deale cruelly with thine owne yoake-fellow, to hate, to reuile, to abuſe thy parents, whom thou oughteſt to loue, honour, and obey, to be with out naturall affection to thine
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:15204:73"/> owne children, who are thine owne bowels, to deale doggedly with thy neere kinred, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindly with thoſe of whoſe kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe thou haſt ſo bountifully ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, is a thing ſo horrible, ſo iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, that I dare warrant thee will coſt ſtings intollerable, yea (without repentance,) wounds of conſcience incurable. For if it <hi>be</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Illa eſt vera inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centia, quae nec inimico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocet. Auguſt. in Pſal.</note> 
               <hi>true innocencie, not to hurt a deadly foe,</hi> then it muſt needs be iniurie in graine to wrong a deere friend; and the greateſt ſinnes muſt haue the greateſt puniſhments, of which puniſhments torture of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is one, yea the greateſt in this life, if it produceth deſpaire, as it many times doth. If therefore it bee thy hap to heare or reade this, who art at enmity with thoſe to whom thou art tyed by the bonds of nature or kindneſſe, let
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:15204:74"/> mee entreate this at thy hands, that thou wouldeſt labour with the ſerious meditation of this, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thine inordinate and violent affections, that it may cauſe thee to relent, for thy former enmitie, and breake in ſunder thoſe barres of contention, whereby thy heart hath beene bolted vp againſt thy brother ſo long a time.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>6</label> 
               <note place="margin">That Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taliation is Gods Law.</note>The fourth point followeth:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That the Lord requites like for like</hi> to the wrong doer. Iuſt as theſe brethren had dealt with <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> ſo (ſo in their owne apprehenſion at leaſt) are they dealt withall them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues; <hi>Therefore is this diſtreſſe come vpon vs.</hi> As we ſowed, ſo we reape, as we meaſured, ſo is it mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured to vs againe. <hi>We looked vpon</hi> Ioſephs <hi>diſtreſſe, this man lookes vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our, wee would not heare our bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſpeaking for himſelfe, this man
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:15204:74"/> now will not heare vs, we carryed home to our father a falſe tale of</hi> Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſephs <hi>death, now (will we, will wee) we ſhall be compelled to carry him too true newes of the bonds of one of our brethren.</hi> If this were not a truth, wherefore was that law of giuing <hi>life for life, eye for eye, tooth for tooth, hand for hand, foote for foote, bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning for burning, wound for wound,</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">Exod. 21.24, 25, 26. Deut. 2.4. Chap. 19, 20. Deut. 19.21.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> It was the decree of the Lord againſt the <hi>Babylonians,</hi> that the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſians,</hi> ſhould deale with them, as they had dealt with the Iſraelites, as appeareth in the booke of <hi>Ieremie. I will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence them according to their deedes, and according to the workes of their owne hands</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">Iere. 25.14.</note>. <hi>Put your ſelues in aray againſt Babylon, all yee that bend the bow, &amp;c. take vengeance vpon her as ſhee hath done, ſo doe vnto her</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">Iere. 50.14, 15.</note>. <hi>As Babylon hath cauſed the
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:15204:75"/> ſlaine of Iſrael to fall, ſo at Babylon ſhall fall the ſlaine of all the earth</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Ier. 5.49.</note>. Much to this effect is that of <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiel: As I liue (ſaith the Lord) I will doe according to thine anger, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the enuy which thou hast vſed out of thy hatred againſt them</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Ezek. 35.11.</note>. Where he threatneth to deale cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elly with the Edomites, as he had dealt vnmercifully with the Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites. The very ſame is repeated by <hi>Obediah</hi> in the 15. and 16. verſes of his propheſie. <hi>As thou haſt done, it ſhall bee done to thee, thy reward ſhall returne vpon thine owne head, for as ye haue drunke vpon mine holy mountaine, ſo ſhall all the heathen drinke continually.</hi> It is not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne what <hi>Samuel</hi> ſaid, and did to <hi>Agag King of Amaleck. As thy ſword made women childleſſe, ſo ſhall thy mother bee childleſſe among wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. And Samuel hewed Agag in
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:15204:75"/> pieces, before the Lord in Gilgal</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">1. Sam. 15.30.</note>. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>
               </label> The ground of this, I take to be the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtributiue iuſtice of God, which is to reward euery man according to his workes, according to that of <hi>Iob, For the worke of a man ſhall he render vnto him, and cauſe euery man to finde according to his waies</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">Iob 34.11.</note>. Now if it be the office of that iuſtice, to deale with men according to their workes, muſt not that man that offereth wrong to his neighbour, looke to meete with the like at the hand of another?<note n="*" place="margin">Preoccu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patio.</note> Vnleſſe hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation, and reſtitution preuent it, he may vndoubtedly looke for it, or elſe for ſome heauier pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment in the ſtead thereof, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther heere, or heereafter.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> What a bridle to curbe our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurious hearts, what a chaine to binde our iniurious hands, what a locke to barre vp the doore of our
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:15204:76"/> lips from vniuſt thoughts, words, and deedes againſt one another; May the ſerious conſideration of this point bee? I perſwade my ſelfe, there is none of vs would be content to haue iniurie offered our ſelues by others: Why, oh why then ſhall wee delight to offer wrong to others, our ſelues? woul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt thou not looſe the life of thy childe? take not away then the life of thy ſeruant, another mans childe. For <hi>Abſolons</hi> blood did pay for <hi>Vriahs</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">2. Sam. 18.14.</note>. Wouldeſt thou not haue the adulterer enter into thy bed? defile not thou the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage bed of thy neighbour, for <hi>Dauids</hi> adulterie committed with <hi>Bathſheba,</hi> was requited with the defiling of his owne concubines by his owne ſonne<note n="x" place="margin">2. Sam. 16.22.</note>. Wouldeſt thou not haue others diſdaine and diſregard thee? diſdaine thou not,
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:15204:76"/> diſregard thou not other men? for if <hi>Iſmaels hand be againſt euery man, euery mans hand ſhall be against him</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">Gen. 16.12.</note>. Wouldeſt thou not haue others ſet traps for thee? ſpread thou no nets, digge thou no pits for another: for if <hi>Haman</hi> ſeekes the ruine of the Iewes, <hi>Esther</hi> ſhall plotte his ouerthrow<note n="z" place="margin">Compare Eſther 3. with Chap. 7.6.</note>. Woul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt thou not haue anothers wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome worke the confuſion? vſe not thy wit for anothers harme: For if <hi>Achitophels</hi> wit bee againſt the Lords <hi>Anoynted, Huſhais</hi> wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome ſhall confound his<note n="a" place="margin">2. Sam. 17.7, 8.</note>. Woul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt thou not be ſlandered? ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der not; wouldeſt thou not bee coſened? deceiue not: wouldeſt thou not be oppreſſed? oppreſſe not: wouldeſt thou not haue an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other man encreaſe his reuenues vpon thy ruine, ſtuffe not thine owne bagges with the beggering
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:15204:77"/> of others: wouldeſt thou not leaue thy wife, thy children, a prey to the extortioners, oppreſſours and cormorants gullet, to haue the ſtate that thou bequeatheſt them, the inheritance thou leaueſt them, deuoured by him, conſumed of him, after thou art dead and gone? robbe not the orphane of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance, deceiue not the widdow of her maintenance, while thou liueſt; for if thou doeſt, their wrongs will cry for vengeance, and neuer lin vntill either in thy ſelfe, or thy ſeede, thou be payed home in the like kinde: wouldeſt thou not haue thy children (if thou haſt or ſhalt haue any) rob thee of the honour they owe thee? cut not thou thy parents ſhort of that dutie thou oweſt them: If thou beeſt vnder their charge, ſhow thy dutie by obeying their command.
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:15204:77"/> If God hath bleſſed thee with the worlds good aboue them, ſhow thy thankfulneſſe, by releeuing their wants. If thou beeft aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to places of honour aboue them, ſhow thy reſpect by reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rencing their perſons, as <hi>Salomon</hi> did <hi>Bathſhebas</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">1. King. 2.19.</note>. If they happe to ſlippe and fall (as the beſt doe) ſhow thy loue by couering their frailties, as <hi>Sem</hi> and <hi>Iaphet</hi> did <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ahs nakedneſſe</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Gen. 9.23.</note>. Otherwiſe, looke for irreuerence, vnnaturall affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, diſobedience, blazing thy faults, from thy children as a iuſt recompence returned vnto thee. Laſtly, wouldeſt thou not haue thy ſeruants vndutifull, vnfaithfull to thee? when thou ſhalt come to haue any vnder thee? deale thou then neither vndutifully nor vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfully with thy maſter. In a word, what we would not that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:15204:78"/> ſhould doe to vs, let vs not doe to them. For euill ſhall be to the euill doer; and the diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue Iuſtice of the Almightie doth meaſure out the like portion to man, that man meaſureth to his brother.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> Secondly, when wrongs are of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered vs in any kinde by others; this ſhould teach vs to examine and try, whither we be not guiltie of offering the like to others. Thou complaineſt peraduenture; <hi>No man ſo deceiued as I am:</hi> but haſt thou not beene a deceiuer thy ſelfe? thou crieſt out, <hi>none ſo ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, ſo diſgraced, oppreſſed vniuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, iniuried as I haue beene;</hi> but haſt not thou ſlandered, diſgraced, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, wronged others? Thou makeſt thy mone, that thou haſt a croſſe yoake-fellow ouer thou hadſt before, before a louing huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band,
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:15204:78"/> now a cruell one, before a kinde curteous wife, now an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde and kirſt one. But how didſt thou vſe thy former yoake-fellow, how dealteſt thou with her, how behaued'ſt thou thy ſelfe towards him? it may be curriſhly, crab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedly. Thou complaineſt of the diſobedience of thy children, how that they will not be conformable to thee, will not be ruled by thee, they are prodigall againſt thy will, marry without thy conſent, and thou canſt not keepe them within compaſſe: Thou complaineſt of the idleneſſe, and vntruſtineſſe of thy ſeruants; except thy eye be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies on them, thou canſt haue no worke done by them, thou dareſt not truſt them, they are ſo lime-fingred, thou dareſt ſcarce ſpeake to them, they are ſo ſaucy tongued. It may be when thou wert in the
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:15204:79"/> condition of a childe, thou wert as diſobedient to thy parents, it may be thou haſt beene out nights and daies in baſe company a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their liking, it may be thou haſt bin ſtubborne at their threats, diſobedient to their voyce, it may be (without all reſpect of pietie and honeſtie) thou didſt match thy ſelfe againſt their liking. Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture, when thou wert a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, thou wert vnruly, vntruſty, idle, ſaucy thy ſelfe. When theſe and the like wrongs cauſe thee to complaine; Pauſe a little with thy ſelfe, and ſay; <hi>Haue not I done thus and thus with others, as others do with mee:</hi> The Lord (thou ſeeſt) doth requite wrong for wrong, into the boſome of the wrong doer; And it may be vpon examination, thou maieſt finde thy ſelfe guiltie of the ſame offence; If thou doeſt, then
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:15204:79"/> giue vnto God the glory of his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtributiue iuſtice, and ſay as <hi>Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibezek</hi> did, when his thumbes and great toes were cut off. <hi>As I haue done, ſo God hath requited me</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Iudg. 1.7.</note>. And if thou haſt not yet repented, or ſo ſoundly repented as thou ſhouldeſt, repent at length and ceaſe to doe euill in that kinde. But if ſo bee vpon examination, thou finde thine owne innocency, or hauing beene ſo guiltie haſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented, and yet art thus and thus wronged ſtill, beare thy croſſe with patience, beſeech God to ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie it vnto thee, to humble thee by it, and make it a preſeruatiue for thee, againſt doing the like wrongs thy ſelfe, though thou ſhouldeſt haue neuer ſo fit occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, neuer ſo ſtrong temptations to the ſame. So much for that do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</p>
            <pb n="142" facs="tcp:15204:80"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>7</label> 
               <note place="margin">They that are pitti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in their miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, others ſhall as lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle pittie them in theirs.</note>The next and laſt thus. <hi>That they ſhall finde little pittie at the hands of others in their diſtreſſe, who haue beene without pittie to their brethren, in the time of their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe.</hi> This could theſe brethren confeſſe heere. That <hi>Ioſephs</hi> pitti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe carriage, (as they receiued it at that time) towards them, was cauſed by their owne want of pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie towards him in the time of his miſery. The comparing of the 137. <hi>Pſalme,</hi> with the thirteenth of <hi>Iſaiah, verſe</hi> 18. will make this good. Out of the former place, wee may gather how pittileſſe to the captiue Iewes, the Babyloni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans were flouting and gibering at them (<note n="c" place="margin">Pſal. 137.3.</note> 
               <hi>Sing vs one of the ſongs of Sion:</hi>) And in the<note n="d" place="margin">Iſa. 13.18</note> latter, we finde how pittileſſe and Medes and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians ſhould be to <hi>THEM,</hi> beeing called vpon by God, by a prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:15204:80"/> Apoſtrophe, <hi>to daſh their yong men to pieces before their eyes, to haue no pittie on the fruits of their wombe, neither ſhould their eye ſpare their little children.</hi> This particular, hath ſome witneſſe, from <hi>Iames</hi> his generall<note n="e" place="margin">Iam. 2.13.</note>; <hi>Hee ſhall haue iudgement without mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, that hath ſhewed no mercie. Becauſe thou haſt ſpoiled many na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> (ſaith <hi>Habakuck</hi> ſpeaking to the cruell Chaldeans) that is pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tileſſely vſed many people, <hi>there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the remnant of the people ſhall ſpoile thee</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Hab. 2.8.</note>, yea deale pittileſſely with thee. For when men fall to the ſpoile, then they rage like wilde beaſts with little pittie, if with any at all.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> A point making much to the terrour of all mercileſſe and pitti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe perſons, who pitty not the wants of them that are in pouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:15204:81"/> who minde not the griefes of them that are in miſery: who threw their brethren into the pit, the priſon for ſmall trifles, and will not bee perſwaded to releaſe them: who haue the cry of the poore at their gates, at their doores, and will not be mooued to releeue them: who heare the newes of the troubles of Gods people at this day, ſounding in their eares, and yet are not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoked to regard them. Is it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probable that theſe men ſhall haue mercie ſhowne them in the time of their miſery? Probable? no, not poſſible, except repentance change them, and compaſſion cloath them to make them better. For if they be bleſſed that are full of <hi>mercie</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Mat. 5.7.</note>, their happineſſe part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſiſting in this, <hi>that they ſhall obtaine mercie,</hi> then they are <hi>wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched</hi>
               <pb n="145" facs="tcp:15204:81"/> who are voyde of pittie, and this is one piece of their wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chedneſſe, that they finde little pittie at the hands either of God or man. Tell mee <hi>(Naball)</hi> if the Lord ſhould euer ſtrip thee of thy abundance (as hee can doe it in a moment, for hee that gaue all can take all at his pleaſure) who thinkeſt thou ſhould ſuccour <hi>thee,</hi> when thou refuſeſt to heare the poore mans crie? Tell me thou <hi>that forgetteſt Ieruſalem,</hi> if the Lord in his iuſt iuſtice ſhould ſuffer thoſe helliſh fire-brands the Ieſui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall faction, to ſet our land on fire, to ſtirre vp ciuill diſſention amongſt vs (as they haue at this day done in <hi>France</hi>) if hee ſhould ſend a fierce nation againſt vs, let in the enemie vpon vs, vnto which and more then which the abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations of the land haue ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:15204:82"/> a wide gap already; what eye (thinkeſt thou) would pittie thee, what hand would ſpare <hi>thee,</hi> when as neither thy heart yearneth, nor eye watreth at the <hi>deſolation of Gods pleaſant portion</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Ierem. 12.10.</note>, at the great affliction of the Lords heritage in our neighbour nations? Tell me thou malicious one (who ſeemeſt to be made all of <hi>Reuenge</hi>) that throweſt thy brother into priſon, (as theſe my text ſpeakes off did <hi>Ioſeph</hi> into a pit) for a dreame, a trifle, that threatneſt to haue his skinne, ſweareſt not to leaue him worth a groate, trounceſt him vp and downe, from poſt to pillar, from court to court, from aſſize to to aſſize, for little or nothing al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt, tell me (I ſay) how lookeſt thou to eſcape the like meaſure? Is there neuer a priſon, neuer a bench, neuer a barre, no like ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamitie,
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:15204:82"/> and rigour of law for thee? Are there not as mercileſſe ones, as pittileſſe ones, to vexe, ſpoile and vndoe thee, vpon as ſlight an occaſion as thou mole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteſt thy brother, if thou doe but giue it? In a word, whoeuer thou beeſt, who putteſt of all pitie, and cloatheſt thy ſelfe with crueltie, is it impoſſible thinkeſt thou, for thee to bee vnmercifully dealt withall thy ſelfe, if thou doeſt, thou art much miſtaken. For (as the<note n="i" place="margin">Senec. de Clemen. l. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>25.</hi> Nam talem vtrums, a tergo ſequi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur everſio, odia venena, gladij.</note> Heathen could tell vs,) <hi>ruine, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, poyſons, ſwords doe follow ſuch an one at the hard heeles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> To adde therefore a word of exhortation and ſo conclude; let vs bee perſwaded to cloath our ſelues with the robes of pittie, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them that are in diſtreſſe: Heare wee others make their moane to vs, others will heare vs
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:15204:83"/> make our moane to them. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue we the wants of others, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers will releeue ours; Mourne for others troubles, others will mourne for ours; Comfort we o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in their ſorrowes, others will comfort vs in ours. If according to the heauenly patterne wee bee mercifull; our heauenly Father will take ſuch order, that pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ſhall be ſhowne vs in middeſt of our aduerſitie.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:15204:83"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
